<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Melpomene: or, The muses delight Being new poems and songs. Written by several of the great wits of our present age, as I.D. T.F. S.W. T.S. C.O. I.B. &amp;c. Collected together, and now printed.</title>
            <title>New collection of poems and songs.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1678</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 152 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 86 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77795</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B5456</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R216784</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99899676</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99899676</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170736</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77795)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170736)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2421:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Melpomene: or, The muses delight Being new poems and songs. Written by several of the great wits of our present age, as I.D. T.F. S.W. T.S. C.O. I.B. &amp;c. Collected together, and now printed.</title>
                  <title>New collection of poems and songs.</title>
                  <author>Bulteel, John, fl. 1683.</author>
                  <author>Rochester, John Wilmot, Earl of Rochester, 1647-1680. aut</author>
                  <author>Owen, Corbett, 1646-1671. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 156, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for H. Rogers at the Bible in Westminster-Hall, against the Court of Common Pleas,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1678.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Collected and edited by John Bulteel.</note>
                  <note>Contains poems by John Wilmot, Earl of Rochester, Corbett Owen, and others.</note>
                  <note>Leaf a3 is mis-signed a2; leaf A1 (bastard title) is cancelled.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: New poems and songs.</note>
                  <note>With a final advertisement leaf.</note>
                  <note>A reissue, with cancel title page, of Wing B5457, i.e. the 1674 edition with Bulteel's name on title page and with title "A new collection of poems and songs".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library, Oxford, England.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>English poetry --  Early modern, 1500-1700 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Songs, English --  Texts --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170736:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170736:1"/>
            <p>MELPOMENE: OR, THE <hi>M<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SES DELIGHT.</hi> Being New POEMS AND SONGS.</p>
            <p>Written by ſeveral of the great Wits of our preſent Age, as <hi>I.D. T.F. S.W. T.S. C.O. I.B. &amp;c.</hi> Collected together, and now Printed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>H. Rogers</hi> at the Bible in <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter-Hall,</hi> againſt the <hi>Court</hi> of <hi>Common Pleas,</hi> 1678.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:170736:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170736:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170736:3"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:170736:3"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:170736:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170736:4"/>
            <head>A TABLE OF All the SONGS and POEMS contained in this Book.</head>
            <list>
               <item>TO his dead Miſtris, at her Tomb. <hi>Page 1</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To the former loving Mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. <hi>8</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>SONG.</label> I grant your eys are much more bright. 13</item>
               <item>
                  <label>SONG.</label> 
                  <hi>Cloris,</hi> 'twill be for eithers reſt. 14</item>
               <item>
                  <label>SONG.</label> I grant, a thouſand oathes I ſwore. 16</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:170736:5"/>
                  <hi>Against Chastity.</hi> 18</item>
               <item>
                  <label>SONG.</label> 
                  <hi>Cloris,</hi> if I forſake you now. 21</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Imperfect Enjoyment</hi> 23</item>
               <item>
                  <label>SONG.</label> Reproach me not, tho heretofore. 26</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Voyage.</hi> 28</item>
               <item>
                  <label>SONG.</label> Blinde Boy, farewel; I laugh at now. 41</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Loves Contentment.</hi> 43</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>To a Coy Lady.</hi> 45</item>
               <item>
                  <label>SONG.</label> 
                  <hi>Cloris,</hi> believe this truth, you cannot move me. 46</item>
               <item>The Review. <hi>To his worthy friend, Dr</hi> William Sandcroft, <hi>Dean of S.</hi> Pauls. 47</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:170736:5"/>
                  <hi>The Schiſmatick.</hi> 59</item>
               <item>
                  <label>SONG.</label> 
                  <hi>Prethee, little Boy, refrain. 62</hi>
               </item>
               <item>News from <hi>Newcaſtle. 64</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To the Dutcheſs of <hi>Cleveland 71</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To a fooliſh Fair one <hi>75</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Fading Beauty. <hi>76</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To a full-grown Beauty. <hi>77</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Enjoyment. <hi>79</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Land-voyage in <hi>Ireland. 91</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To a fair Miſtris <hi>97</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Against Women. <hi>99</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Anſwer,</hi> in defence of Women. <hi>103</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Fooliſh Nicety <hi>107</hi>
               </item>
               <item>On the Victory over the <hi>Spaniards</hi> in the Bay of <hi>Sancta Crux,</hi> in the Iſland
<pb facs="tcp:170736:6"/>
of <hi>Tenariff. 109</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the ſight of a fair Ladies breech, diſcovered at her being turned over in a Coach. <hi>Tranſlated out of French. 117</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the Intolerable Heat in the later end of <hi>May,</hi> and the beginning of <hi>June, 1665. 121</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poems">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170736:6"/>
            <head>New Poems AND SONGS.</head>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>To his Dead Miſtriſs at her Tomb.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>WIth bowed thoughts, low as this hollow Cell,</l>
                  <l>Where thy warm youth eternally muſt dwell:</l>
                  <l>With Eyes out-vying this curl'd Marbles ſweat,</l>
                  <l>(My treaſures proud uſurping Cabinet)</l>
                  <l>With the poor heart, which once thou gav'ſt relief,</l>
                  <l>And that poor heart fir'd with all zealous grief,</l>
                  <l>I come to parley with thy Sacred Clay,</l>
                  <l>And with thy Ghoſt hold mournful Holy-day;</l>
                  <l>To offer on this place where thou'rt inſhrin'd</l>
                  <l>This ſigh, more churliſh than the Southern wind,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="2" facs="tcp:170736:7"/>Whoſe perſume ſhall mount heaven, and there controul</l>
                  <l>The ſwift departure of thy winged Soul.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Pale Maid, far whiter than the milky way</l>
                  <l>Which now thou tread'ſt; or if I all may ſay,</l>
                  <l>Fair as thou living wert; What erring hand</l>
                  <l>Hath carry'd thee into this ſilent Land?</l>
                  <l>Who cropt the Roſe and Lilly from thy face,</l>
                  <l>To plant in this ſame dull and barren place,</l>
                  <l>Where nothing, like thy ſelf, can ever riſe,</l>
                  <l>Although I daily water't with mine Eyes?</l>
                  <l>Say, (thou who didſt of late to me appear</l>
                  <l>Brighter than <hi>Titan</hi> in our Hemiſphear)</l>
                  <l>What ſullen change hath thus Eclipſed thee,</l>
                  <l>And caſt this Earth betwixt thine Eyes and me?</l>
                  <l>Adulterous Feaver, worſe than <hi>Tarquins</hi> brood,</l>
                  <l>Who mixt thy luſtful heat with her warm blood?</l>
                  <l>Who ſent, who fann'd the flames to ſuch a height</l>
                  <l>Within her veins, as did burn out her light?</l>
                  <l>'Twas not thy work, great Love, thy active darts</l>
                  <l>Convey no burning Feavers to our hearts;</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="3" facs="tcp:170736:7"/>But move in blood-warm fires, whoſe livelihood</l>
                  <l>By calm degrees ripens the tender bud</l>
                  <l>Of pure affections. If the Rule be ſure,</l>
                  <l>That Souls do follow bodies temp'rature,</l>
                  <l>Then by her purer Soul I may conclude</l>
                  <l>That not the leaſt diſtemper durſt intrude</l>
                  <l>Upon her body, no <hi>Criſis</hi> could be,</l>
                  <l>For that there was ſuch perfect harmony</l>
                  <l>In her bleſt Fabrick, as if Nature had</l>
                  <l>Weigh'd out the ſweet materials ere ſhe clad</l>
                  <l>Her in her fleſhly Robe. I oft have read</l>
                  <l>Gods have their heavenly Thrones abandoned,</l>
                  <l>And feign'd mortality, to compaſs ſo</l>
                  <l>Our brighter ſhining heavens here below,</l>
                  <l>Women. Sure it was ſo; ſome higher power</l>
                  <l>Looking from off his all-commanding Tower,</l>
                  <l>Firſt on our conſtant Love, then on thy Face,</l>
                  <l>Grew proud to Rival me, envy'd my place,</l>
                  <l>Came cloathed all in flames, and Courted thee,</l>
                  <l>As erſt the Thunderer did <hi>Semele:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="4" facs="tcp:170736:8"/>Laying her fate on thee to dye i'th' place,</l>
                  <l>And be conſumed in the hot embrace:</l>
                  <l>Whil'ſt I that once enjoy'd a libertie</l>
                  <l>Kings could not claim, to love and honour thee,</l>
                  <l>And knew my ſelf to be above the ſtrain</l>
                  <l>Of our beſt Monarchs to be lov'd again,</l>
                  <l>Now 'reſt of all, can unto nought aſpire</l>
                  <l>But theſe ſad Reliques of my former fire:</l>
                  <l>Theſe aſhes in this leaden ſheet enroll'd</l>
                  <l>Cold as my bitter hopes, oh! bitter cold!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Pretty Corruption! that I ſighing cou'd</l>
                  <l>Breath life in thee, or weeping ſhowre warm blood</l>
                  <l>Into thy veins! for I do envy thee</l>
                  <l>Thy Crown of Bliſs, now thou art t'ane from me.</l>
                  <l>My griefs run high, and my diſtracted brain</l>
                  <l>Like the wing'd billows of the angry Main,</l>
                  <l>When it attempts to flie into the Air,</l>
                  <l>Falls into thouſand drops of moiſt deſpair.</l>
                  <l>'Tis true, thou living wert as gently calm</l>
                  <l>As Lovers whiſpers, or a Sea of balm:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="5" facs="tcp:170736:8"/>Yet, when I think that all this now is duſt,</l>
                  <l>The fancy breaks upon me, like the guſt</l>
                  <l>Of a high-going Sea, whoſe fury threats</l>
                  <l>More than my reaſon well can brook, and beats</l>
                  <l>Her wounded Ribs; this muſt a Wrack portend,</l>
                  <l>Or ſure ſome proneneſs to a deſperate end!</l>
                  <l>It calls me Coward, and to that does add,</l>
                  <l>Falſe-hearted lover, that at leaſt ne'r had</l>
                  <l>Spark of a Turtles fire; whoſe patience</l>
                  <l>Can brook the World, now thou art t'ane from hence.</l>
                  <l>It wrongs my breaſt, gives my true heart the lye,</l>
                  <l>And ſayes I never lov'd, I dare not dye.</l>
                  <l>And yet I dare! — I dare an inroad make</l>
                  <l>Upon the tedious breath which now I take:</l>
                  <l>I could out-work Times Sickle; I could mow</l>
                  <l>My blooming youth down even at one blow;</l>
                  <l>Which he hath labour'd at, but yet not done</l>
                  <l>So many births of the renewing Sun.</l>
                  <l>I have keen ſteel, and a reſolved Arm</l>
                  <l>Back'd by deſpair, and grief to any harm.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="6" facs="tcp:170736:9"/>But ſhould I ſtrike, Dear, thou wouldſt vail thy Face</l>
                  <l>With thy white Robe, and bluſh me to a place</l>
                  <l>VVhere nought was ever heard but ſhreeks and howls</l>
                  <l>Of the condemned, and tormented Souls.</l>
                  <l>No, when my eyes glance here, and view how ſtill</l>
                  <l>This ſprightly Peer now lies, the ſight does chill</l>
                  <l>My deſperate fury, and a Chriſtian fear</l>
                  <l>Commands me quench this wild-fire with a tear.</l>
                  <l>This very touch of thy cold hand does ſwage</l>
                  <l>My hot deſign and irreligious rage.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But, 'tis not manners thus to keep thee from</l>
                  <l>The ſilent quiet of <hi>Elizium.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I will but add a word or two, and then</l>
                  <l>Caſt thee into thy long dead-ſleep agen.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Your favour, holy linnen, happy Shrowd,</l>
                  <l>(For I muſt draw away this ſnowy cloud</l>
                  <l>From off her whiter face) and witneſs now</l>
                  <l>Ye Gods, unto an Orphan Lovers vow.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>By theſe blind <hi>Cupids,</hi> theſe two Springs of light</l>
                  <l>Now hood-wink't in the endleſs maſque of night:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="7" facs="tcp:170736:9"/>By this well-ſhapen promont, whoſe ſmooth end</l>
                  <l>Like to a mount of Ivory doth bend</l>
                  <l>Toward this Red-ſea, upon whoſe Corral-ſhore</l>
                  <l>I had rich Traffick once, but never more</l>
                  <l>Muſt deal in: By thy ſelf, and if there were</l>
                  <l>A better thing for me, by that I'd ſwear,</l>
                  <l>That thou ſhalt not, (like others,) lie and rot</l>
                  <l>With thy fair name, fair as thy ſelf, forgot;</l>
                  <l>But thy Idea ſhall inform my brains</l>
                  <l>Like the Intelligence that holds the reins</l>
                  <l>Of both the Orbs; I will not know the day,</l>
                  <l>But as it hath a luſtre like the ray</l>
                  <l>Of thy bright Eye; and when the Night is come,</l>
                  <l>'Tis like the quiet of thy ſilent Tomb.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Laſt, I will only live to grief, and be</l>
                  <l>Thy Epitaph unto Poſteritie;</l>
                  <l>That whoſo ſees me, reads, <hi>Yonder ſhe lies,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>For whom this widdow'd Lover ever dies.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And witneſs Heaven, now I this Oath have took,</l>
                  <l>I kiſs, and ſhut, the Alabaſter-Book.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:170736:10"/>
               <head>To the former loving Mourner.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THou doſt invite me by thy ſolemn Knell</l>
                  <l>Of Love and Sorrow, to Ring out my Bell,</l>
                  <l>Which is ſo out of Tune this doleful way,</l>
                  <l>Hang me i'th' Rope, if I know what to ſay.</l>
                  <l>Could want of knowledge, — in a various ſence</l>
                  <l>On my part, — wait on her departure hence,</l>
                  <l>Or guſh a Torrent full of grief, — like thine,</l>
                  <l>No Muſe might urge a juſter plea than mine.</l>
                  <l>For, — ſhe's abſtracted ignorance, — poor thing!</l>
                  <l>Both what ſhe ſhould, — and how ſhe ought to ſing:</l>
                  <l>Nor is ſhe one of that th'row pacing-Tribe,</l>
                  <l>As will be ſpurr'd to ſob, or howl for Bribe,</l>
                  <l>Or Cuſtom, — like the <hi>Iriſh</hi> at a Grave,</l>
                  <l>Or peeviſh Wives, — if curb'd of what they crave:</l>
                  <l>My eyes, — too coſtive to bedew a Herſe,</l>
                  <l>Wring out their tears, as hard as they do Verſe;</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:170736:10"/>And this is it, that makes me ſeem ſo fine,</l>
                  <l>And ſo abſtemious of the Sad-Grave's Wine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Beſides this Sacred Text, — thou doſt retrieve,</l>
                  <l>And handles, — Dead ſo well, — how e're alive,</l>
                  <l>That by the Dirge thou ſing'ſt, — And that kind vow</l>
                  <l>Thou mak'ſt t' Eternize her, — we muſt allow</l>
                  <l>Her Excellence ſuch a ſublime degree,</l>
                  <l>As her offended Eye diſpleas'd would be</l>
                  <l>To read anothers Line, beſides thine own</l>
                  <l>Unto her memory, — or on the Stone.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And what am I, — alas! — that I ſhould dare</l>
                  <l>To write, — where equal ſuch perfections are?</l>
                  <l>No, — no, — I know my verge, — I ken how far</l>
                  <l>Rules the poor feeble influence of my Star.</l>
                  <l>Which, — like ſome Meteor, — might a while reſent</l>
                  <l>The common-gazer, — but is now quite ſpent.</l>
                  <l>Some honeſt Countrey-Girl,—perhaps — whoſe face</l>
                  <l>Chooſes the next clear Current for her Glaſs,</l>
                  <l>And ſimp'ring dyes a Maid,—or very ne're,</l>
                  <l>(As in an Age ſome Miracles appear:)</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="10" facs="tcp:170736:11"/>Or ſome Retailers iſſue of the Town,</l>
                  <l>VVho ſinks for envy at the next new Gown</l>
                  <l>She ſees, and cannot reach; may me prefer</l>
                  <l>To be her ſad Fates doubty Chronicler,</l>
                  <l>Or ſo; theſe dead aſleep, may keep awake</l>
                  <l>My Muſe, or elſe the wanton does partake</l>
                  <l>Much of our Peaſants humour here, who ſay</l>
                  <l>VVhen bid to work it's ſome ſtrange Holy-day.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yet, I am none of that ungracious H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rd,</l>
                  <l>That at anothers loſs, ſit down unſtir'd,</l>
                  <l>Or elſe all-arm'd with ſuch glad ſcorn, can be</l>
                  <l>Drunk with the tears of others miſerie;</l>
                  <l>VVhen at ſome petty loſs themſelves ſuſtain,</l>
                  <l>You'd think the Deluge were on float again.</l>
                  <l>A loving ſympathy within me dwells,</l>
                  <l>And, like thy Miſtriſs, though thy grief excells</l>
                  <l>All tribute elſe, which all thy Friends can pay,</l>
                  <l>My little Rivulet attends thy Sea:</l>
                  <l>Though like ſmall Brooks, much ſhallow noiſe it keep,</l>
                  <l>VVhen Rivers are moſt ſilent, are moſt deep.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:170736:11"/>
                  <l>VVho would not hazard Credit, Life and all,</l>
                  <l>To ſecond ſuch a Loyal Principal,</l>
                  <l>As here thou prov'ſt, ſince a ſmall time diſcovers</l>
                  <l>How full of Changes are the moſt of Lovers?</l>
                  <l>VVhil'ſt thine eternal Love goes on, and ends</l>
                  <l>Not with her end, but time's laſt wings aſcends!</l>
                  <l>How will the Beauties, that of this ſhall hear,</l>
                  <l>Trick up themſelves, and ſtrive to be thy dear?</l>
                  <l>And ſuch as dealt in Rivalſhip, before,</l>
                  <l>VVill ſeem, at leaſt, this paſſage to deplore!</l>
                  <l>To loſe a Miſtriſs in her prime, and one</l>
                  <l>So qualify'd as thine! 't would force a groan</l>
                  <l>From the rough quarry of rebellious hearts,</l>
                  <l>And his, with pity that as ſeldom parts,</l>
                  <l>As with the rights of others, though he tread</l>
                  <l>Strange paths, if once poſſeſſion he can plead.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But, oh the grief! to ſee a Virgin laid</l>
                  <l>Like wax diſſolv'd, yet no impreſſion made!</l>
                  <l>Her flowry bloſſom, ſuch a Froſt to meet,</l>
                  <l>And for a Bridal, find a Winding-ſheet!</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:170736:12"/>Can youth, — and beauty, — no exemption have,</l>
                  <l>Ye deſtinies, — from an untimely Grave?</l>
                  <l>Take old ones,-let them march,-what make they here?</l>
                  <l>But to raiſe Taxes,—and make Victuals dear:</l>
                  <l>To ſcold at all,—but what themſelves have ſeen</l>
                  <l>In ſuch a year of <hi>James,</hi> — Or th' Maiden Queen;</l>
                  <l>Find fault with Patches, and Black-bags in ſcorn,</l>
                  <l>And cry, — 'Twas a good time when Ruffs were worn,</l>
                  <l>And Plackets ſlit before, — not this new way,</l>
                  <l>As if they fancy'd <hi>Italy</hi>'s foul Play.</l>
                  <l>Away with theſe, — for Pity ſpare the reſt;</l>
                  <l>Theſe are, as good for Worms-meat, as the beſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>A real Sadneſs, — I do now put on,</l>
                  <l>When I but think on thee, — and who is gone.</l>
                  <l>For thou haſt thrown thy ſelf before her Tomb</l>
                  <l>So moiſt a Sacrifice, — and art become</l>
                  <l>Such a ſurviving Monument — as we</l>
                  <l>Find fewer ſighs to ſpend on Her, — than Thee.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="song">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:170736:12"/>
               <head>SONG.</head>
               <lg n="1">
                  <head>I.</head>
                  <l>I Grant your Eyes are much more bright</l>
                  <l>Than ever was unclouded light:</l>
                  <l>And that love in your charming voyce</l>
                  <l>As much of Reaſon finds for choice.</l>
                  <l>Yet if you hate when I adore,</l>
                  <l>To do the like I find much more.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="2">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <l>A voyce would move all but a ſtone,</l>
                  <l>Without kind love ſhall find me one:</l>
                  <l>And Eyes the brighteſt ever ſhin'd</l>
                  <l>On me have pow'r, but as their kind:</l>
                  <l>You muſt to throw down all defence,</l>
                  <l>As much my Reaſon pleaſe as Senſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="3">
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:170736:13"/>
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <l>I clearly know, ſay what you will,</l>
                  <l>To read my heart you want the skill:</l>
                  <l>And of this 'tis a pregnant ſigne,</l>
                  <l>Since you ſee not theſe truths of mine;</l>
                  <l>Which if you did, you would deſpair</l>
                  <l>Without your Love to form one there.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="song">
               <head>SONG.</head>
               <lg n="1">
                  <head>I.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>CLoris,</hi> 'twill be for eithers reſt,</l>
                  <l>Truly to know each others breaſt:</l>
                  <l>I'll make th' obſcureſt part of mine</l>
                  <l>Tranſparent as I would have thine.</l>
                  <l>If you will deal but ſo with me,</l>
                  <l>We ſoon ſhall part, or ſoon agree.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="2">
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:170736:13"/>
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <l>Know then, though you were twice as fair,</l>
                  <l>If it could be, as now you are;</l>
                  <l>And though the Graces of your Minde</l>
                  <l>With a reſembling luſtre ſhin'd:</l>
                  <l>Yet if you love me not, you'll ſee</l>
                  <l>I'll value thoſe as you do me.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="3">
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <l>Though I a thouſand times had ſworn</l>
                  <l>My paſſion ſhould tranſcend your ſcorn,</l>
                  <l>And that your bright triumphant eyes</l>
                  <l>Create a Flame that never dies;</l>
                  <l>Yet if to me you prov'd untrue,</l>
                  <l>Thoſe Oathes ſhould turn as falſe to you.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="4">
                  <head>IV.</head>
                  <l>If I vow'd to pay Love for Hate,</l>
                  <l>'Twas, I confeſs, a meer deceit;</l>
                  <l>Or that my Flame ſhould deathleſs prove,</l>
                  <l>'Twas but to render ſo your Love:</l>
                  <l>I brag'd as Cowards uſe to do</l>
                  <l>Of dangers they'll ne'r run into.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="5">
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:170736:14"/>
                  <head>V.</head>
                  <l>And now my Tenents I have ſhow'd,</l>
                  <l>If thou think them too great a Load;</l>
                  <l>T'attempt your change, were but in vain,</l>
                  <l>The Conqueſt not being worth the pain.</l>
                  <l>With them I'll other Nymphs ſubdue;</l>
                  <l>'Tis too much to loſe time, and you.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="song">
               <head>SONG.</head>
               <lg n="1">
                  <head>I.</head>
                  <l>I Grant, a thouſand oathes I ſwore</l>
                  <l>I none would love but you:</l>
                  <l>But not to change would wrong me more</l>
                  <l>Than breaking them can do.</l>
                  <l>Yet you thereby a truth will learn,</l>
                  <l>Of much more worth than I;</l>
                  <l>Which is, That Lovers which do ſwear,</l>
                  <l>Do alſo uſe to lie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="2">
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:170736:14"/>
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cloris</hi> does now poſſeſs that heart</l>
                  <l>Which to you did belong:</l>
                  <l>But, though thereof ſhe brags a while,</l>
                  <l>She ſhall not do ſo long.</l>
                  <l>She thinks by being fair and kinde,</l>
                  <l>To hinder my remove,</l>
                  <l>And ne'r ſo much as dreams that Change</l>
                  <l>Above both thoſe, I love.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="3">
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <l>Then grieve not any more, nor think</l>
                  <l>My change is a diſgrace:</l>
                  <l>For though it robs you of one Slave,</l>
                  <l>It leaves anothers place:</l>
                  <l>Which your bright eyes will ſoon ſubdue</l>
                  <l>With him does them firſt ſee:</l>
                  <l>For if they could not conquer more,</l>
                  <l>They ne'r had conquer'd me.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:170736:15"/>
               <head>Againſt CHASTITY.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>COld Chaſtneſs, ſhould I praiſe thee, when thou art</l>
                  <l>Natures great'ſt errour, and canſt claim no part</l>
                  <l>In her intentions, which doth ſtill produce</l>
                  <l>Creatures for propagation, and for uſe?</l>
                  <l>All other Prodigies which here are ſeen,</l>
                  <l>Partake ſome eſſence which is rang'd between</l>
                  <l>Two divers kindes, or joyn two kindes in one:</l>
                  <l>But this is ſuch a Monſter as hath none.</l>
                  <l>Nor doth this Rule deceive us, or miſlead,</l>
                  <l>Apply'd to Mindes, although ſome intercede</l>
                  <l>'Twixt two Opinions, others them confound</l>
                  <l>To ſome new Paradox: yet none is found</l>
                  <l>So groſly ſtupid, wholly to exclude</l>
                  <l>All ſort of ſenſe. Do then no more delude</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:170736:15"/>With vain appearances, when thou within</l>
                  <l>Art rebel unto Nature, and doſt ſin</l>
                  <l>Againſt thy own Creation, and contend,</l>
                  <l>All that thou canſt, the World by thee ſhould end.</l>
                  <l>So that in vain Heav'ns light ſhould ſhine or heat;</l>
                  <l>In vain the Horſe ſhould neigh, the Ram ſhould bleat;</l>
                  <l>In vain the Stag ſhould bray, the Bird ſhould ſing;</l>
                  <l>In vain the Graſs ſhould grow, the Herb ſhould ſpring,</l>
                  <l>When their kindes grew unnatural and wild,</l>
                  <l>And Procreation were from Earth exil'd.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I damn not yet, a Chaſtneſs which doth riſe</l>
                  <l>From ſuch a conſtant Love as makes one prize</l>
                  <l>Some perſons more than others: theſe effects</l>
                  <l>Are Loves prerogatives, which ſo connects</l>
                  <l>Two hearts, as they appropriate a right</l>
                  <l>Elſe common unto all: let ſuch delight</l>
                  <l>In one another ſtill; onely that heart</l>
                  <l>Which cannot finde a reaſon to impart</l>
                  <l>It ſelf to any, doth to me appear</l>
                  <l>So much enormous, I may juſtly fear</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:170736:16"/>To be a greater Criminal than thoſe</l>
                  <l>Who rob and kill: for though by them men loſe;</l>
                  <l>Their lives remainder, what they had, or did,</l>
                  <l>Yet ſtill is theirs: But Chaſtneſs doth forbid</l>
                  <l>All life at once. Beſides, Thieves often win</l>
                  <l>By acting miſchief: But this Monſter-ſin</l>
                  <l>Getting nought, but a falſe pretext to ſtrike</l>
                  <l>Even at Lifes root, cauſleſs ſupplants alike</l>
                  <l>Both good and bad. Again, the Murtherer can</l>
                  <l>Repair his loſs, and get another man:</l>
                  <l>But Chaſtneſs labours even to hide the Mould</l>
                  <l>In which he ſhould be fram'd, and gladly would</l>
                  <l>(Th'rough a ſubverting of all humane ſtate)</l>
                  <l>At once leave Earth and Heaven deſolate.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now, if this be the moſt deſtructive ill</l>
                  <l>In either Sex, ſince they are thought to kill</l>
                  <l>Who may and will not ſave; 'tis greateſt ſure</l>
                  <l>In thoſe are fair: we eaſier can endure</l>
                  <l>This fault in any elſe, and better taſte</l>
                  <l>The Foul and Wanton, than the Fair and Chaſte.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="21" facs="tcp:170736:16"/>For who thinks Rich and Miſerable ſute?</l>
                  <l>Who cares for Orators when they are mute?</l>
                  <l>What doth avail a Balm which none applies?</l>
                  <l>And who eſteems a Beauty that denies?</l>
                  <l>Let Chaſtneſs, then, in the unſound and old,</l>
                  <l>The Pregnant, Marry'd, Vow'd, ill-favour'd Scold,</l>
                  <l>Not be diſlik'd: But, in the fair and free,</l>
                  <l>Let it be thought the greateſt Crime can be;</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Since being 'gainſt Natures chief end oppos'd,</l>
                  <l>It ſeems, in it, all other Vice is clos'd.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="song">
               <head>SONG.</head>
               <lg n="1">
                  <head>I.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>CLoris,</hi> if I forſake you now,</l>
                  <l>And to ſome meaner Empire bow;</l>
                  <l>Think not your Beauty I deſpiſe,</l>
                  <l>Or ſlight the ſplendour of your Eyes:</l>
                  <l>All the exceptions I can finde</l>
                  <l>Is, That you are more fair than kinde.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="2">
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:170736:17"/>
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <l>What though your Beauty do tranſcend,</l>
                  <l>All Love-ſick Poets ſo commend?</l>
                  <l>Yet foul and willing have more taſte</l>
                  <l>Than very fair, and over-chaſte.</l>
                  <l>And who'd not ſtoop to common fare,</l>
                  <l>Rather than feed too long on Air?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="3">
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <l>Should I in vain ſtill thus purſue,</l>
                  <l>'Twere onely to loſe time and you:</l>
                  <l>And a ſmall fort I'd rather get,</l>
                  <l>Than onely to beſiege a great:</l>
                  <l>Long time too much of youth would waſte;</l>
                  <l>How ſhould I man it well at laſt?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="4">
                  <head>IV.</head>
                  <l>Beauty does joy to th'eye diſpenſe,</l>
                  <l>But Kindneſs raviſhes each Senſe:</l>
                  <l>'Tis dull to have one ſenſe invited</l>
                  <l>Alone, where all ſhould be delighted.</l>
                  <l>Enjoyment feaſteth every one:</l>
                  <l>I muſt, I muſt feed all, or none.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:170736:17"/>
               <head>The IMPERFECT ENJOYMENT.</head>
               <l>FRuition was the Queſtion in debate,</l>
               <l>Which like ſo hot a Caſuiſt I did ſtate,</l>
               <l>That ſhe with freedom urg'd as my offence,</l>
               <l>To teach my Reaſon to ſubdue my Senſe.</l>
               <l>But yet this angry Cloud which did proclaim</l>
               <l>Vollies of Thunder, melted into Rain;</l>
               <l>And this adulterate Stamp of ſeeming nice,</l>
               <l>Made feigned Vertue but a Bawd to Vice.</l>
               <l>For by a Complement that's ſeldome known,</l>
               <l>She thruſts me out, and yet invites me home:</l>
               <l>And thoſe delays do but advance delight,</l>
               <l>As Prohibition ſharpens Appetite.</l>
               <l>For the kinde Curtain raiſed my eſteem</l>
               <l>To wonder at the opening of the Scene,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:170736:18"/>When of her breſts her hands the Guardians were,</l>
               <l>Yet I ſalute each ſullen Officer,</l>
               <l>Though like the flaming Sword before mine eyes,</l>
               <l>They block the paſſage to my Paradiſe.</l>
               <l>Nor could thoſe Tyrant-hands ſo guard the Coyn,</l>
               <l>But Love, where't cannot purchaſe, may purloyn.</l>
               <l>For though her breſts be hid, her lips are prize,</l>
               <l>To make me rich beyond my avarice;</l>
               <l>Yet my ambition my affection fed</l>
               <l>To conquer both the White Roſe and the Red.</l>
               <l>Th'event prov'd true: for on the Bed ſhe ſate,</l>
               <l>And ſeem'd to covet, what ſhe ſeem'd to hate:</l>
               <l>Heat of reſiſtance hath increas'd her fire,</l>
               <l>And weak defence is turn'd to ſtrong deſire.</l>
               <l>What unkinde influence could interpoſe,</l>
               <l>When two ſuch Stars did in Conjunction cloſe?</l>
               <l>Onely too haſtie zeal my hopes did foil;</l>
               <l>Preſſing to feed her Lamp, I ſpilt my Oil:</l>
               <l>And, that (which moſt reproach upon me hurl'd)</l>
               <l>Was dead to her, gives life to all the world:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:170736:18"/>Natures chief Prop, and Motions primeſt Source,</l>
               <l>In me both loſt their figure, and their force.</l>
               <l>Sad Conqueſt! when it is the Victors fate</l>
               <l>To die at th'entrance of the opening gate!</l>
               <l>Like prudent Corporations, had we laid</l>
               <l>A Common Stock by, we'd improv'd our Trade:</l>
               <l>But as a Prodigal Heir, I ſpent by th' by,</l>
               <l>What home directed wou'd ſerve her and I.</l>
               <l>When next on ſuch aſſaults I chance to be,</l>
               <l>Give me leſs vigour, more activitie:</l>
               <l>For Love turns impotent when ſtrain'd too high;</l>
               <l>His very Cordials make him ſooner die:</l>
               <l>Evaporates in Fume the fire too great:</l>
               <l>Loves Chymiſtry thrives beſt in equal heat.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="song">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:170736:19"/>
               <head>SONG.</head>
               <lg n="1">
                  <head>I.</head>
                  <l>REproach me not, though heretofore</l>
                  <l>I onely Freedom did adore;</l>
                  <l>And brag that none, though kinde as fair,</l>
                  <l>The loſs of it could half repair:</l>
                  <l>Since now I willingly do yield</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Cloris</hi> beauty all the field.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="2">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <l>With greater joys I do reſigne</l>
                  <l>My freedom, than thou ere keptſt thine;</l>
                  <l>And am reſolv'd conſtant to prove,</l>
                  <l>Should her neglect tranſcend my love.</l>
                  <l>Strange Charms they are that make me burn,</l>
                  <l>Without the hopes of a return.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="3">
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <l>To ſee, and not to be in love,</l>
                  <l>A wonder like her ſelf would prove;</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="27" facs="tcp:170736:19"/>Whoſe Charms by Nature and by Art</l>
                  <l>Do each of them deſerve a heart.</l>
                  <l>For which my ſorrows are but ſmall,</l>
                  <l>I have but one to pay them all.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="4">
                  <head>IV.</head>
                  <l>I muſt confeſs, a while I ſtrove</l>
                  <l>With Reaſon to reſiſt my Love.</l>
                  <l>The Saints ſometimes 'gainſt death do pray,</l>
                  <l>Though 't be to Heav'n their onely way.</l>
                  <l>'Tis onely <hi>Cloris</hi> hath the skill</l>
                  <l>To make me bleſt againſt my will.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="5">
                  <head>V.</head>
                  <l>Nor will I ſo much as endure</l>
                  <l>To think Inconſtancie a Cure:</l>
                  <l>For were I to that ſin ſo bent,</l>
                  <l>It ſure would prove my Puniſhment.</l>
                  <l>For to adore, I muſt confeſs,</l>
                  <l>Is better than elſewhere ſucceſs.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:170736:20"/>
               <head>The VOYAGE.</head>
               <lg n="1">
                  <head>I.</head>
                  <l>AS one that's from a tedious Voyage come,</l>
                  <l>And ſafe th'rough thouſand ſtorms arriv'd at home,</l>
                  <l>Reſolves to put to Sea no more,</l>
                  <l>Or boldly tempt the flatt'ring Main,</l>
                  <l>How ſmoothe ſoere it lie, or plain;</l>
                  <l>But having drawn his broken Hull on ſhore,</l>
                  <l>To ſome kinde Saint hangs up his conſecrated Oar:</l>
                  <l>I, who a greater Sea had paſt,</l>
                  <l>The Ocean of rough Poeſie,</l>
                  <l>Where there ſo many ſhipwrackt be,</l>
                  <l>Or on the Rocks, or on the Quickſands caſt;</l>
                  <l>Recounting what my ſelf had ſeen,</l>
                  <l>And in how many deaths I had been,</l>
                  <l>Where ſcarce an empty wiſh or hope could come between.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:170736:20"/>With almoſt as confirm'd a Vow,</l>
                  <l>Reſolv'd no leſs to conſecrate</l>
                  <l>Some Votive Table, which might ſhow</l>
                  <l>The Labours I did undergo;</l>
                  <l>And at a far more eaſie rate,</l>
                  <l>Give others the delight to view on Land my dangerous Fate.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="2">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <l>Already was the ſacred Plank deſign'd,</l>
                  <l>And in it how I firſt aſſay'd the Deep,</l>
                  <l>When thinking onely neer the Shores to keep,</l>
                  <l>There roſe a ſudden and tempeſtuous winde,</l>
                  <l>Which made me leave the unſaluted Land behinde.</l>
                  <l>The Sea before was calm, and ſtill,</l>
                  <l>And gentle Airs did with my Streamers play,</l>
                  <l>Scarce ſtrong enough my half-ſtruck Sail to fill,</l>
                  <l>And th'rough the yeelding Chriſtal force my way.</l>
                  <l>Cloſe by did many a Veſſel ride,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe Pilots all with Bays were gayly crown'd,</l>
                  <l>And to the murmurs of the Tyde,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:170736:21"/>Voices and Mirth were heard around,</l>
                  <l>My ſelf made there <hi>Anacreons</hi> Lute reſound;<note place="margin">Turn'd <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacreon</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Engliſh Verſe.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which ſprightly ſeem'd, &amp; wondrous brave,</l>
                  <l>And its old killing Notes to have;</l>
                  <l>But from the waters more than thoſe rough touches which I gave.</l>
                  <l>'Twould ſtill of nothing ſound but Love,</l>
                  <l>Though I the various Stops did often prove:</l>
                  <l>Wherefore new Loves I did begin,<note place="margin">Made ſeveral Love-verſes to <hi>Cletia &amp; al.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>And intermixt (as parts) my own;</l>
                  <l>Which took freſh vigour from the String,</l>
                  <l>And o'er the dancing Flouds were quickly blown.</l>
                  <l>I <hi>Venus</hi> ſang, and ſtolen joys,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Tranſlated</hi> 4 <hi>Book</hi> Virg</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>And of his Flames who ſcap'd at <hi>Troys.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And as the Thracian <hi>Orpheus</hi> by his skill</l>
                  <l>To ranſome his <hi>Euridice</hi> is ſed,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Claudians</hi> Rapt. Proſ</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>And from the Shades brought back the dead;</l>
                  <l>My Song a greater Miracle did tell,</l>
                  <l>And thither chain'd in Verſe alive <hi>Proſerpina</hi> did lead.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="3">
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:170736:21"/>
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <l>Such was my Song: but when the Storm aroſe,</l>
                  <l>Voyces and mirth were heard no more,</l>
                  <l>But every man fell ſtoutly to his Oar,</l>
                  <l>And to the flouds did all their ſtrength oppoſe,</l>
                  <l>Hoping to reach ſome Harbour, but in vain;</l>
                  <l>They were with greater fury hurry'd back into the Main.</l>
                  <l>Then might one hear in ſtead of theſe,</l>
                  <l>The dying ſhreeks of ſuch as ſhipwrackt were;</l>
                  <l>And thoſe proud Galleys, which before at eaſe</l>
                  <l>Plow'd up the Deep, no longer did appear;</l>
                  <l>But to the waves became a Prey:</l>
                  <l>Some downright ſank, ſome broken lay,</l>
                  <l>And by the billows were in triumph born away.</l>
                  <l>My Keel ſo many Leaks did ſpring,</l>
                  <l>That all the Hold with water was flow'd o'er;</l>
                  <l>And a Sea no leſs dangerous rag'd within,</l>
                  <l>Than that which ſtrove abroad the tempeſt to outroar.<note place="bottom">Having had ſo many Croſſes, or, which is truer, ſeeing the little profit, I reſolved to make no more Verſe, except the argument were Divine or Moral; and ſo reſumed my old deſigne of Paraphraſing the Pſalms<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Which I began anew, <hi>Jan. 31. 1662.</hi> and finiſht the <hi>3</hi> of <hi>June 1665.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:170736:22"/>So over-board my lading ſtraight I caſt,</l>
                  <l>With ſome faint hopes my Barque to ſave;</l>
                  <l>But on the wind away they quickly paſt,</l>
                  <l>And my beſt ſafety was no hope to have.</l>
                  <l>Yet by me ſtill the great <hi>Jeſſean</hi> Lyre I kept,</l>
                  <l>Which from my Couch I down did take,</l>
                  <l>Where it neglected long enough had ſlept,</l>
                  <l>And all its numerous Chords I did awake;</l>
                  <l>Thinking, ſince I the waves muſt try,</l>
                  <l>Them and the Sea-gods with a Song to pacifie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="4">
                  <head>IV.</head>
                  <l>I play'd, and boldly then plung'd down,</l>
                  <l>Holding my Harp ſtill in my hand,</l>
                  <l>My dear Companion through thoſe paths unknown;</l>
                  <l>But hopeleſs with it ere to reach the Land,</l>
                  <l>When lo, the chaſte <hi>Iarma,</hi> with a throng</l>
                  <l>Of Nymphs and Tritons waited on,</l>
                  <l>As ſhe by chance there paſs'd along,</l>
                  <l>Drave up her Chariot by my ſide,</l>
                  <l>And in requital for my humble Song,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:170736:22"/>Invited me with her to ride,</l>
                  <l>And fearleſs of the way, with them my courſe to guide.</l>
                  <l>And down ſhe reach'd her Snowie hand,</l>
                  <l>And from the flouds me gently rais'd,</l>
                  <l>Whilſt all the Sea-gods on me gaz'd,</l>
                  <l>And waited, ere they further went, ſome new Command.</l>
                  <l>Which ſtraight ſhe gave, and at her word the winde</l>
                  <l>Backward did ſcowre: before, as ſmoothe and plain</l>
                  <l>The Ocean lay; ſtorms onely rag'd behinde:</l>
                  <l>So to my Harp I turn'd again,</l>
                  <l>And all its ſilent fetters did unbinde.</l>
                  <l>No longer was I of the Deep afraid,</l>
                  <l>But bolder grown, more Anthems plaid,</l>
                  <l>And on them put my Chains, who theirs upon the waves had laid.</l>
                  <l>Till having many a Country paſt,</l>
                  <l>And coaſting the whole earth around,</l>
                  <l>The Northweſt paſſage navigable found,</l>
                  <l>I on my native ſhore was caſt,</l>
                  <l>And ſafely toucht the <hi>Britiſh</hi> Iſle at laſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="5">
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:170736:23"/>
                  <head>V.</head>
                  <l>This Table as in Colours 'twas expreſt,</l>
                  <l>And which <hi>Beliſa</hi>'s curious Pencil wrought,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mris</hi> Mary Beal.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>With Ivie Garlands and with Bays I dreſt,</l>
                  <l>And to my Muſes ſacred Temple brought;</l>
                  <l>Hoping it would accepted be,</l>
                  <l>And ſurely gain my liberty</l>
                  <l>From future ſervice, and declare me free.</l>
                  <l>But as I waiting in the Court did ſtand,</l>
                  <l>Into a ſudden extaſie I fell;</l>
                  <l>And led by an Immortal hand,</l>
                  <l>Which entrance for me did command,</l>
                  <l>Approacht the Fanes moſt private Cell</l>
                  <l>By none ere ſeen before, where awful dread and reverence dwell.</l>
                  <l>'Twas not like thoſe ſtrait lodges here,</l>
                  <l>Which by that name we call,</l>
                  <l>But a magnificent and ſpacious Hall,</l>
                  <l>The Roof with Paintings garniſht all;</l>
                  <l>And where in Neeches on the wall,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="35" facs="tcp:170736:23"/>There did the lively forms appear</l>
                  <l>Of ſuch who for their Verſe the Laurel Sert did wear.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Greece</hi> and old <hi>Rome</hi> poſſeſt the chiefeſt place,</l>
                  <l>And all the upper end their quarter was:</l>
                  <l>The ſides were into ſeveral Coaſts deſign'd,</l>
                  <l>And by their Countries you each name might finde;</l>
                  <l>Th' <hi>Italian, French,</hi> or <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Band,</l>
                  <l>As they around did with their Titles ſtand:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Britain</hi> as fair a ſpace as any had;</l>
                  <l>And no leſs honors were to her, than <hi>Rome</hi> or <hi>Athens</hi> paid.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="6">
                  <head>VI.</head>
                  <l>Thither I turn'd my eye, and in the throng</l>
                  <l>Of Crowned heads tranſlated there,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe very Names to count would be too long,</l>
                  <l>The bright <hi>Orinda</hi> did appear;<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mris</hi> Kath. Philips <hi>died</hi> June 64.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>And though come thither laſt of all,</l>
                  <l>Made the moſt beauteous Figure on the ſacred wall.</l>
                  <l>Aſide her ſeveral Neeches were prepar'd</l>
                  <l>For thoſe who ſhall hereafter come,</l>
                  <l>And with her there obtain a room,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="36" facs="tcp:170736:24"/>As with her in the Muſes ſervice they had ſhar'd.</l>
                  <l>Already were ſome names enrol'd,</l>
                  <l>And in fair characters inchas'd;</l>
                  <l>But who they were, muſt ne'r be told,</l>
                  <l>Till they the fatal ſtream have paſt,</l>
                  <l>And after death have here their living Statues plac't.</l>
                  <l>My Muſe alone theſe Worthies could outſhine,</l>
                  <l>As ſhe approacht me there in ſhape divine:</l>
                  <l>Her golden hair was all unbound</l>
                  <l>With careleſs art, and wantonly did play,</l>
                  <l>Mov'd by her ſtrings Melodious ſound,</l>
                  <l>As on her ſhoulders the looſe treſſes lay.</l>
                  <l>A wondrous Mantle o'er her back was thrown,</l>
                  <l>And her gay myſtick Veſt below</l>
                  <l>In Royal ſtate trayl'd all adown;</l>
                  <l>A Lute was in her hand, and on her head a Crown.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="7">
                  <head>VII.</head>
                  <l>Amaz'd, I at her feet did fall,</l>
                  <l>And proſtrate lay, till up ſhe bid me ſtand,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:170736:24"/>Saying, For this I thee did never call,</l>
                  <l>But boldly to receive my great Command.</l>
                  <l>Ariſe, for lo, a better fate</l>
                  <l>Does on thy tuneful Numbers wait,</l>
                  <l>Than what thou in the Deep haſt try'd of late.</l>
                  <l>Not but that all thy labours there,</l>
                  <l>To thine own wiſh ſhall amply be repaid.</l>
                  <l>For I by whom enroll'd they are,</l>
                  <l>Second to none but Heav'n in that great care</l>
                  <l>Which of thy Verſe and thee I always had,</l>
                  <l>Will look ſuch large allowance for them ſhall be made,</l>
                  <l>That all the damage which thou didſt ſuſtain,</l>
                  <l>Shall not compare with thy immortal gain.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="8">
                  <head>VIII.</head>
                  <l>Witneſs thy Votive Table, which I h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re accept</l>
                  <l>Within my Archives a fair room to have,</l>
                  <l>(Worthy for th' hand that did it to be kept)</l>
                  <l>And thy mean Name from dark oblivion ſave,</l>
                  <l>Till to another Temple, that's above,</l>
                  <l>Reſerv'd for thoſe, who ſacred Numbers prove,</l>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:170736:25"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:170736:25"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="38" facs="tcp:170736:26"/>And there at laſt conclude their love.</l>
                  <l>Thy ſouls bright Image I hereafter ſhall remove,</l>
                  <l>Where ſeveral whom thou here doſt know</l>
                  <l>(Ambitious at their very Shrines to bow)</l>
                  <l>Leaving their wanton Lays behinde,</l>
                  <l>Like thee, and from all baſe Alloy refin'd,</l>
                  <l>More to reſemble the Eternal minde;</l>
                  <l>With ſeveral who were never here,</l>
                  <l>So God-like all their Meaſures were,</l>
                  <l>(As <hi>Jeſſe</hi>'s ſon, whoſe Harp thou erſt didſt bear)</l>
                  <l>In glory with the firſt great Maker ſhine,</l>
                  <l>And have for Mortal Bays, a Ray Divine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="9">
                  <head>IX.</head>
                  <l>But firſt, my <hi>Silvius,</hi> thou again to Sea muſt go,</l>
                  <l>And many Towns, and Men, and Countries know,</l>
                  <l>In the New-world of Chriſtian Poeſie,<note place="margin">To write of the Creation never attempted by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Engliſhman except in Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Part of which long ſince was deſign'd to be</l>
                  <l>The happie fruits of thy diſcovery;</l>
                  <l>Where none of all thy Nation has been yet,</l>
                  <l>The way ſo dangerous, and the task ſo great.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="39" facs="tcp:170736:26"/>Nor doubt but it ſhall recompence thy coſt;</l>
                  <l>And were it more, that age, they cry, th'aſt loſt,</l>
                  <l>When to ſerve me, thou didſt the Bar forſake,<note place="margin">The ſtudy of the Law.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>And for th' Long Robe, the Ivie Garland take,</l>
                  <l>As that which would thy Name immortal make.</l>
                  <l>For I have Honours to beſtow,</l>
                  <l>And Regal Treaſures, though I rarely ſhow</l>
                  <l>The happie Country where they grow.</l>
                  <l>And though ſome wretch the Plague endure</l>
                  <l>Of miſerable Poverty,</l>
                  <l>The fault's his own, and not in me;</l>
                  <l>Not that he is my Votary,</l>
                  <l>But under that diſguiſe an Enemy:</l>
                  <l>Not I, but they alone who count me ſo, are poor.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="10">
                  <head>X.</head>
                  <l>Try me, this once, and once more tempt the Main;</l>
                  <l>Thou ſhalt not unattended go:</l>
                  <l>For when thou next putſt out to Sea again,</l>
                  <l>I'll be thy Pilot, and the paſſage ſhow.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="40" facs="tcp:170736:27"/>Nay wonder not, for 'tis no more</l>
                  <l>Than what I ſeveral times have done before,</l>
                  <l>When I my <hi>Taſſo</hi> through thoſe Straights did guide,</l>
                  <l>And made my <hi>Bartas</hi> o'er the Surges ride;</l>
                  <l>Thoſe mighty Admirals which did extend</l>
                  <l>Their Country-bounds beyond the worlds wide end:</l>
                  <l>'Twas I conducted them thoſe Lands to finde,</l>
                  <l>Where each did plant their Nations Colonies;</l>
                  <l>Both ſpreading leſs their Sayls than Victories.</l>
                  <l>And there are yet more Lands for thee behinde;</l>
                  <l>And all the way, like them, thou ſhalt rehearſe</l>
                  <l>The Birth of things, how they from nothing roſe,</l>
                  <l>By that Almighty Word which ſhall inſpire thy Verſe,</l>
                  <l>And help thee all its Wonders to diſcloſe.</l>
                  <l>No Storm upon thy Maſt ſhall reſt,</l>
                  <l>Or any Gales but Vernal blow;</l>
                  <l>The Sea it ſelf, to my great ſervice preſt,</l>
                  <l>In plains of liquid Glaſs ſhall lie below,</l>
                  <l>And its obedience to my Rule in dancing billows onely ſhow.</l>
                  <l>And when thou home return'd ſhalt be,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="41" facs="tcp:170736:27"/>And of thy native earth once more take hold,</l>
                  <l>My ſelf thy Barque will conſecrated ſee;</l>
                  <l>And for this new World thus found out by thee,</l>
                  <l>Make it an heav'nly Signe, neer that which ſav'd the old.</l>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>S.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="song">
               <head>SONG.</head>
               <lg n="1">
                  <head>I.</head>
                  <l>BLinde Boy, farewel; I laugh at now</l>
                  <l>That pow'r to which I once did bow:</l>
                  <l>For Reaſon hath the Throne regain'd,</l>
                  <l>Where Paſſion that Uſurper raign'd.</l>
                  <l>An Idol th'art, and ſo men uſe thee;</l>
                  <l>Fools do adore, the Wiſe abuſe thee.</l>
                  <l>Beauty alone, which conquers many,</l>
                  <l>On me hath little pow'r, if any.</l>
                  <l>My fault would be great as thy Blindneſs,</l>
                  <l>Should I love Beauty without Kindneſs.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="2">
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:170736:28"/>
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <l>Tyrant, who never yet wert known</l>
                  <l>To torture any but thy own;</l>
                  <l>To reſiſt thee needs little skill:</l>
                  <l>For he hath pow'r, that hath but will.</l>
                  <l>He that hath been mad, or a Lover,</l>
                  <l>Believes neither, if he recover:</l>
                  <l>Whilſt we our ſelves are, we defie thee;</l>
                  <l>None which are ſo, are conquer'd by thee:</l>
                  <l>Thy art is all in taking ſeaſon,</l>
                  <l>When we believe Senſe, more than Reaſon.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:170736:28"/>
               <head>Loves Contentment.</head>
               <lg n="1">
                  <head>I.</head>
                  <l>COme, my <hi>Olympia,</hi> we'll conſume</l>
                  <l>Our Joys no more at this low rate;</l>
                  <l>More glorious Titles let's aſſume,</l>
                  <l>And love according to our ſtate.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="2">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <l>For if Contentment be a Crown</l>
                  <l>Which never Tyrant could aſſail;</l>
                  <l>How many Monarchs put me down</l>
                  <l>In their <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>topian</hi> Commonweal?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="3">
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <l>As Princes rain down golden ſhowres</l>
                  <l>On thoſe in whom they take delight:</l>
                  <l>So in this happier ſtate of ours,</l>
                  <l>Each is the others Favourite.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="4">
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:170736:29"/>
                  <head>IV.</head>
                  <l>Our privacie no eye dwells neer,</l>
                  <l>But unſuſpected we'll embrace;</l>
                  <l>And no ſlick Courtiers Pen is there,</l>
                  <l>To ſet down either time or place.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="5">
                  <head>V.</head>
                  <l>We'll fear no Enemies invaſion,</l>
                  <l>But being wiſe and politique,</l>
                  <l>With timely force, if not perſwaſion,</l>
                  <l>We'll cool the home-bred Schiſmatique.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="6">
                  <head>VI.</head>
                  <l>No jealous fears ſhall thwart our bliſs,</l>
                  <l>Unleſs a golden dream awake us:</l>
                  <l>For Care, we'll not know what it is,</l>
                  <l>Unleſs to pleaſe doth careful make us.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="7">
                  <head>VII.</head>
                  <l>All diſcontent thus to remove,</l>
                  <l>What Monarch boaſts, but thou and I?</l>
                  <l>In this content we'll live and love,</l>
                  <l>And in this love reſolve to die.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:170736:29"/>
               <head>To A Coy LADY.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>WHy ſo Fair, and yet ſo Cruel?</l>
                  <l>What is Beauty, but Loves fuel?</l>
                  <l>What's, without a Stone, a Jewel?</l>
                  <l>Sure that Faulcon needs muſt Mew ill,</l>
                  <l>That not open keeps her Tuil.</l>
                  <l>Do not think that I purſue ill,</l>
                  <l>Or, in ſaying ſo, think you ill.</l>
                  <l>Why ſo fair, and yet ſo Cruel?</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="song">
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:170736:30"/>
               <head>SONG.</head>
               <lg n="1">
                  <head>I.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>CLoris,</hi> believe this truth, you cannot move me,</l>
                  <l>Though I deny not you are charming fair:</l>
                  <l>No, you muſt love me,</l>
                  <l>Or you muſt deſpair</l>
                  <l>A heart under your Empire for to bring,</l>
                  <l>Where Reaſon's King.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="2">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <l>And yet I do confeſs that never any</l>
                  <l>Was in your flames ſo apt to burn as I;</l>
                  <l>That you have many</l>
                  <l>Charms can make me die:</l>
                  <l>But all thoſe loſe their power, until I ſee</l>
                  <l>You burn with me.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:170736:30"/>
               <head>The Review. To his worthy Friend Dr. <hi>WILL. SANDCROFT,</hi> Dean of St. <hi>Pauls.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>WHen firſt I ſtept into th'alluring Maze,</l>
                  <l>To tread this Worlds myſterious waies,</l>
                  <l>Alas! I had no guide nor clue;</l>
                  <l>No <hi>Ariadne</hi> lent her hand;</l>
                  <l>Not one of Virtues Guards did bid me ſtand,</l>
                  <l>Or askt me, what I meant to do?</l>
                  <l>Or, whither I would go?</l>
                  <l>The Labyrinth ſo pleaſant did appear,</l>
                  <l>I loſt my ſelf with much content,</l>
                  <l>Infinite hazards underwent;</l>
                  <l>Outſtragled <hi>Homer</hi>'s crafty Wanderer,</l>
                  <l>And ten years more than he in fruitleſs travel ſpent.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="48" facs="tcp:170736:31"/>The one half of my life is gon,</l>
                  <l>The ſhadow the Meridian paſt;</l>
                  <l>Death's diſmal evening drawing on,</l>
                  <l>Which will with miſts and damps be overcaſt:</l>
                  <l>An evening which will ſurely come:</l>
                  <l>'Tis time, high time to give my ſelf the welcom home.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="2">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <l>Had I but heartily believ'd</l>
                  <l>All that the Royal Preacher ſaid was true,</l>
                  <l>When firſt I entred on the Stage,</l>
                  <l>And Vanity ſo hotly did purſue;</l>
                  <l>Convinc'd by his experience, not my age,</l>
                  <l>I had my ſelf long ſince retriev'd:</l>
                  <l>I ſhould have let the Curtain down</l>
                  <l>Before the Fools part had begun.</l>
                  <l>But I, throughout the tedious Play have bin</l>
                  <l>Concern'd in every Scene:</l>
                  <l>Too too inquiſitive, I try'd</l>
                  <l>Now this, anon another face,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="49" facs="tcp:170736:31"/>And then a third more odde took place;</l>
                  <l>Was every thing, but what I was.</l>
                  <l>This was my <hi>Protean</hi> Folly, this my pride,</l>
                  <l>Befool'd through all the Tragi-Comedy,</l>
                  <l>Where others meet with hiſſing, to expect a <hi>Plaudite.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="3">
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <l>I had a minde the Paſtoral to prove,</l>
                  <l>Searching for happineſs in Love;</l>
                  <l>And finding <hi>Venus</hi> painted with a Dove,</l>
                  <l>A little naked Boy hard by;</l>
                  <l>The Dove which has no gall,</l>
                  <l>The Boy no dangerous Arms at all:</l>
                  <l>They do thee, great Love, ſaid I,</l>
                  <l>Much wrong. Great Love ſcarce had I ſpoke,</l>
                  <l>Ere into my unwary boſome came</l>
                  <l>An unextinguiſhable flame;</l>
                  <l>From my <hi>Amyra</hi>'s eyes the Lightning came,</l>
                  <l>Which left me more than Thunder-ſtruck;</l>
                  <l>She carries Tempeſt in that lovely name.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="50" facs="tcp:170736:32"/>Loves mighty and tumultuous pain,</l>
                  <l>Diſorders Nature like a Hurricane:</l>
                  <l>Yet could not believe ſuch ſtorms could be</l>
                  <l>When I launcht forth to Sea;</l>
                  <l>Promis'd my ſelf a calm and eaſie way,</l>
                  <l>Though I had ſeen before</l>
                  <l>Pitious ruines on the ſhore;</l>
                  <l>And on the naked Beach <hi>Leander</hi> ſhipwrackt lay.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="4">
                  <head>IV.</head>
                  <l>To extricate my ſelf from love,</l>
                  <l>Which I could ill obey, but worſe command,</l>
                  <l>I took my Pencils in my hand;</l>
                  <l>With that Artillery for Conqueſt ſtrove:</l>
                  <l>Like wiſe <hi>Pigmaleon</hi> then did I</l>
                  <l>My ſelf deſigne my Deity;</l>
                  <l>Made my own Saint, made my own Shrine;</l>
                  <l>If ſhe did frown, one daſh would make her ſmile<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>All bickerings one eaſie ſtroke would reconcile:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Plato</hi> ſeign'd no Idea ſo divine.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="51" facs="tcp:170736:32"/>Thus did I quiet many froward day,</l>
                  <l>While in my eyes my ſoul did play:</l>
                  <l>Thus did the time, and thus my ſelf beguile;</l>
                  <l>Till on a time, and then I knew not why,</l>
                  <l>A tear faln from my eye</l>
                  <l>Waſht out my Saint, my Shrine, my Deity.</l>
                  <l>Prophetick chance! the lines are gone,</l>
                  <l>And now I mourn o're what I doted on:</l>
                  <l>I find even <hi>Gioto</hi>'s Circle has not all perfection:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="5">
                  <head>V.</head>
                  <l>To Poetry I then enclin'd,</l>
                  <l>Verſe that emancipates the mind,</l>
                  <l>Verſe that unbinds the Soul,</l>
                  <l>That amulet of ſickly fame;</l>
                  <l>Verſe that articulates Name;</l>
                  <l>Verſe for both fortunes, apt to ſmile and to condole.</l>
                  <l>Ere I had long the trial made,</l>
                  <l>A ſerious thought made me afraid;</l>
                  <l>For I had heard <hi>Parnaſſus</hi> ſacred Hill.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:170736:33"/>Was ſo prodigiouſly high,</l>
                  <l>Its barren top ſo neer the skie;</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Aether</hi> there</l>
                  <l>So very pure, ſo ſubtil, and ſo rare,</l>
                  <l>'Twould a Cameleon kill,</l>
                  <l>The Beaſt that is all lungs, and feeds on air.</l>
                  <l>Poets the higher up the hill they go,</l>
                  <l>Like Pilgrims ſhare the leſs of what's below.</l>
                  <l>Hence 'tis they go repining on,</l>
                  <l>And murmur more than their own <hi>Helicon.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I heard them curſe their Stars in ponderous Rhimes,</l>
                  <l>And in grave Numbers grumble at the Times:</l>
                  <l>Yet where th' Illuſtrious <hi>Cowly</hi> led the way,</l>
                  <l>I thought it great diſcretion there to go aſtray.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="6">
                  <head>VI.</head>
                  <l>From Liberal Arts to the litigious Law,</l>
                  <l>Obedience, not Ambition did me draw:</l>
                  <l>I lookt at awful Coyf and Scarlet-Gown</l>
                  <l>Through others Opticks, not my own.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="53" facs="tcp:170736:33"/>Unty the <hi>Gordian</hi>-knot who will,</l>
                  <l>I found no Rhetorique at all</l>
                  <l>In them that learnedly could brawl,</l>
                  <l>And fill with Mercenary breath the ſpacious Hall.</l>
                  <l>Let me be peaceable, let me be ſtill:</l>
                  <l>The ſolitary <hi>Thisbite</hi> heard the wind</l>
                  <l>With ſtrength and violence combin'd,</l>
                  <l>That rent the Mountains, and did make</l>
                  <l>The ſolid earths foundation ſhake:</l>
                  <l>He ſaw the dreadful fire, and heard the horrid noiſe,</l>
                  <l>But found whom he expected in the ſmall ſtill voice.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="7">
                  <head>VII.</head>
                  <l>Nor here did my unbridled Fancie reſt,</l>
                  <l>But muſt try</l>
                  <l>A pitch more high,</l>
                  <l>To read the Starry language of the Eaſt,</l>
                  <l>And with <hi>Chaldean</hi> Curioſity</l>
                  <l>Preſum'd to ſolve the Riddle of the Skie;</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="54" facs="tcp:170736:34"/>Impatient till I knew my doom,</l>
                  <l>Dejected till the good direction come;</l>
                  <l>I ript up Fates forbidden womb.</l>
                  <l>Nor would I ſtay till it brought forth</l>
                  <l>An eaſie and a natural birth;</l>
                  <l>But was ſollicitous to know</l>
                  <l>The yet miſhapen <hi>Embryo.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Prepoſterous Crime!</l>
                  <l>Without the formal midwifery of time,</l>
                  <l>Fond man, as if too little grief were given</l>
                  <l>On Earth, draws down inquietudes from Heaven;</l>
                  <l>Permits himſelf with fear to be unman'd,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Balſhazzar</hi>-like grown wan and pale,</l>
                  <l>His very heart begins to fail,</l>
                  <l>Is frighted at the writing of the hand,</l>
                  <l>Which yet nor we, nor all our learn'd Magicians underſtand.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="8">
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:170736:34"/>
                  <head>VIII.</head>
                  <l>And now at length, what's the reſult of all,</l>
                  <l>Should the ſtrict Audit come,</l>
                  <l>And for th'Account too early call?</l>
                  <l>A numerous heap of Cyphers would be found the total Sum.</l>
                  <l>When incompaſſionate age ſhall plough</l>
                  <l>The delicate <hi>Amyra</hi>'s brow,</l>
                  <l>And draw his furrows deep and long;</l>
                  <l>What hardy youth is he,</l>
                  <l>Will after that a Reaper be,</l>
                  <l>Or ſing the Harveſt-ſong?</l>
                  <l>And what is Verſe, but an effeminate vent</l>
                  <l>Either of Luſt or Diſcontent?</l>
                  <l>Colours muſt ſtarve, and all their glories dye;</l>
                  <l>Invented only to deceive the eye:</l>
                  <l>And he that wily Law does love,</l>
                  <l>Much more of Serpent has than Dove.</l>
                  <l>Ther's nothing in Aſtrology</l>
                  <l>But Delphick ambiguity.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="56" facs="tcp:170736:35"/>We are miſguided in the dark, and thus</l>
                  <l>Each Star becomes an <hi>Ignis fatuus.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Yet pardon me, ye glorious Lamps of light;</l>
                  <l>'Twas one of you that led the way,</l>
                  <l>Diſpell'd the gloomy night,</l>
                  <l>Became a <hi>Phoſphor</hi> to th'Immortal day,</l>
                  <l>And ſhew'd the <hi>Magi</hi> where th'Almighty Infant lay.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="9">
                  <head>IX.</head>
                  <l>At length the doubtful Victory's won;</l>
                  <l>It was a cunning Ambuſcade</l>
                  <l>The World for my felicities had laid:</l>
                  <l>Yet now at length the day's our own;</l>
                  <l>Now Conqueror, let us new Laws ſet down;</l>
                  <l>Henceforth ſhall all our love Seraphick turn:</l>
                  <l>The ſprightly and the vigorous flame</l>
                  <l>On th' Altar ſhall for ever burn,</l>
                  <l>And ſacrifice its ancient name.</l>
                  <l>A Tablet on my heart next I'll prepare,</l>
                  <l>Where I will draw the holy Sepulchre;</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="57" facs="tcp:170736:35"/>Behinde it a fair Landskip I will lay</l>
                  <l>Of melancholy <hi>Golgotha:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>On th' Altar I will all my Spoils lay down,</l>
                  <l>And (if I had one) there I'd hang my Lawrel Crown.</l>
                  <l>Give me the Pandects of the Law divine,</l>
                  <l>Such 'twas made <hi>Moſes</hi> face to ſhine.</l>
                  <l>Thus beyond <hi>Saturn</hi>'s heavie Orb I'll tower,</l>
                  <l>And laugh at his malicious power.</l>
                  <l>Raptur'd in Contemplation thus I'll go,</l>
                  <l>Above unactive earth, and leave the Stars below.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="10">
                  <head>X.</head>
                  <l>Toſt on the wings of every winde,</l>
                  <l>After theſe hov'rings to and fro,</l>
                  <l>And ſtill the waters higher grow;</l>
                  <l>Not knowing where, a reſting place to finde,</l>
                  <l>Whither for Sanctuary ſhould I go,</l>
                  <l>But, Revered Sir, to you?</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="58" facs="tcp:170736:36"/>You that have triumpht o're th'impetuous flood,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Noah</hi>-like, in bad times durſt be good,</l>
                  <l>And the ſtiff torrent manfully withſtood,</l>
                  <l>Can ſave me too,</l>
                  <l>One that have long in fear of drowning bin,</l>
                  <l>Surrounded by a Cataclyſme of ſin:</l>
                  <l>Do you but reach out a propitious hand,</l>
                  <l>And charitably take me in,</l>
                  <l>I will not yet deſpair to ſee dry land.</l>
                  <l>'Tis done, and I no longer fluctuate,</l>
                  <l>I've made the Church my Ark, and <hi>Sion</hi>'s Hill my <hi>Ararat.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:170736:36"/>
               <head>THE SCHISMATICK.</head>
               <lg n="1">
                  <head>I.</head>
                  <l>THough now th'Epiſcoparian pow'rs</l>
                  <l>Have rais'd agen this Church of ours,</l>
                  <l>And wilful oppoſites do bring</l>
                  <l>I'th, circle of the Wedding-ring;</l>
                  <l>Yet my <hi>Clarina,</hi> I've a trick</l>
                  <l>To play loves various Schiſmatick.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="2">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <l>Nor will I conſtantly reſpect</l>
                  <l>This Novelty, or that old Sect;</l>
                  <l>But take the freedom ſtill to range,</l>
                  <l>And be a <hi>Proteus</hi> in my change:</l>
                  <l>I'le turn to all the Sects that be,</l>
                  <l>Yet never turn, my Love, from thee.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="3">
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:170736:37"/>
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <l>A Papiſt I will firſt begin:</l>
                  <l>For Love is but a Venial ſin.</l>
                  <l>His Holineſs i'th' Porphyry Chair</l>
                  <l>Gets Neece or Nephew for his Heir:</l>
                  <l>Who calls it Vice, does it miſcal;</l>
                  <l>For 'tis a Vertue Cardinal.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="4">
                  <head>IV.</head>
                  <l>Next, though, indeed, I know there be</l>
                  <l>No Penance like Presbytery,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe rigid and imperious Sway</l>
                  <l>Would force the Monarch to obey:</l>
                  <l>Thy Faith ſhall make, when cloſe we meet,</l>
                  <l>My Works do Penance in a ſheet.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="5">
                  <head>V.</head>
                  <l>An Independent I'll appear</l>
                  <l>To any Love but thine, my Dear:</l>
                  <l>Our wing'd affection we'll advance</l>
                  <l>Above all Forms and Ordinance;</l>
                  <l>Nor outward Rites affect I can,</l>
                  <l>But thou ſhalt feel the inward man.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="6">
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:170736:37"/>
                  <head>VI.</head>
                  <l>The Ranter I will ſmartly play,</l>
                  <l>To fright all Rivals elſe away.</l>
                  <l>An Adamite I needs muſt prove</l>
                  <l>With thee, my Family of Love;</l>
                  <l>Where freely we, to move delights,</l>
                  <l>Will uſe a thouſand pretty ſlights.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="7">
                  <head>VII.</head>
                  <l>A Seeker pleaſes next my minde,</l>
                  <l>'Cauſe what I ſeek I'm ſure to finde.</l>
                  <l>Like Anabaptiſt, who'd not ſtrip</l>
                  <l>In ſuch a pleaſant Bath to dip,</l>
                  <l>Till we lockt in embracing Charms,</l>
                  <l>Turn Quakers in each others Arms?</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="song">
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:170736:38"/>
               <head>SONG.</head>
               <lg n="1">
                  <head>I.</head>
                  <l>PRethee, little Boy, refrain,</l>
                  <l>'Tis in vain</l>
                  <l>That thou at my heart doſt aim:</l>
                  <l>For kind <hi>Bacchus</hi> does ſo charm it,</l>
                  <l>Nought but Wine,</l>
                  <l>Nought but Wine can ever warm it.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="2">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <l>Tell me not of Ladies eyes;</l>
                  <l>I deſpiſe</l>
                  <l>All flames which from thence ariſe:</l>
                  <l>The higheſt loves ere yet created,</l>
                  <l>Are by Wine,</l>
                  <l>Are by Wine, quench'd or abated.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="3">
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:170736:38"/>
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <l>I ſhould Women Tyrants find,</l>
                  <l>If I whin'd</l>
                  <l>When to me they prove unkind:</l>
                  <l>The firſt coldneſs I diſcover,</l>
                  <l>I cure one,</l>
                  <l>I cure one heat by another.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="4">
                  <head>IV.</head>
                  <l>After I my flame relate,</l>
                  <l>If ſhe hate,</l>
                  <l>I uſe her too at that rate:</l>
                  <l>For 'tis always my deſire</l>
                  <l>To do like,</l>
                  <l>To do like her I admire.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="5">
                  <head>V.</head>
                  <l>Therefore though you were more fair</l>
                  <l>Than you are,</l>
                  <l>If unkind, I would not care.</l>
                  <l>Nothing more or leſs can move me</l>
                  <l>To love you,</l>
                  <l>To love you, then you to love me.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:170736:39"/>
               <head>News from <hi>Newcaſtle.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>ENgland</hi>'s a perfect World, has <hi>Indies</hi> too;</l>
                  <l>Correct your Maps, <hi>Newcaſtle</hi> is <hi>Peru:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Let haughty <hi>Spaniards</hi> triumph till 'tis cold;</l>
                  <l>Our ſooty Minerals purifie his Gold.</l>
                  <l>This will ſublime and hatch th'abortive Oare,</l>
                  <l>When the Sun tires, and Stars can do no more.</l>
                  <l>No Mines are currant, unrefin'd and groſs;</l>
                  <l>Coals make the Sterling, Nature but the Droſs.</l>
                  <l>For Metals, <hi>Bacchus</hi>-like, two births approve,</l>
                  <l>Heaven's heats the <hi>Semele,</hi> and ours the <hi>Jove.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thus Art does poliſh Nature, 'tis the trade;</l>
                  <l>So every Madam has a Chamber-maid.</l>
                  <l>Who'd dote on Gold, a thing ſo ſtrange and odd?</l>
                  <l>'Tis moſt contemptible when made a God.</l>
                  <l>All ſin and miſchiefs it does raiſe and ſwell;</l>
                  <l>One India more would make another Hell.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="65" facs="tcp:170736:39"/>Our Mines are innocent, nor will the North</l>
                  <l>Tempt frail mortality with too much worth.</l>
                  <l>Their Art ſo precious, rich enough to fire</l>
                  <l>A Lover, yet make no Idolater.</l>
                  <l>The moderate value of our guiltleſs Ore,</l>
                  <l>Makes no man Atheiſt, nor no woman Whore.</l>
                  <l>Yea, why ſhould hallow'd Veſtals ſacred Shrine</l>
                  <l>Deſerve more honour than a flaming Mine?</l>
                  <l>Theſe pregnant Wombs of heat would fitter be,</l>
                  <l>Than a few Embers for a Deity.</l>
                  <l>Had he our Pits, the Perſian would admire</l>
                  <l>No Sun, but warm's devotion at our fire:</l>
                  <l>He'd leave the rambling Traveller, and prefer</l>
                  <l>Our profound <hi>Vulcan</hi> above <hi>Phoebus</hi> Car.</l>
                  <l>For, wants he Heat, or Light, or would have ſtore</l>
                  <l>Of both? 'tis here: and what can th'Sun give more?</l>
                  <l>Nay, what's the Sun, but in a different Name,</l>
                  <l>A nobler Coal-pit, or a Mine of Flame?</l>
                  <l>Then let this truth reciprocally run.</l>
                  <l>The Sun's Heavens Coalery, and Coals our Sun:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="66" facs="tcp:170736:40"/>A Sun that ſcorcheth not, lock'd up i'th' deep;</l>
                  <l>The Lion's chain'd, the Bandog is aſleep.</l>
                  <l>That Tyrant-fire which uncontroul'd does rage,</l>
                  <l>Is here confin'd, like <hi>Bajazeth</hi> in's Cage:</l>
                  <l>For in each Coal pit there does couchant dwell</l>
                  <l>A muzled <hi>Aetna,</hi> or an innocent Hell;</l>
                  <l>That Cloud but kindled, light you'l ſoon deſcry,</l>
                  <l>Then will a Day break from the gloomy Sky;</l>
                  <l>Then you'l unbutton, though <hi>December</hi> blow,</l>
                  <l>And ſweat i'th' midſt of Icicles and Snow:</l>
                  <l>The Dog-days then at <hi>Chriſtmaſs;</hi> thus is all</l>
                  <l>The year made <hi>June</hi> and Aequinoctial.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If heat offend, our Pits afford you ſhade;</l>
                  <l>The Summer's Winter, Winter's Summer made.</l>
                  <l>A Coal-pit's both a Ventiduct and Stove;</l>
                  <l>What need we Baths? we need no Bower nor Grove.</l>
                  <l>Such Pits and Caves were Palaces of old,</l>
                  <l>Poor Innes, God wot, yet in an age of Gold;</l>
                  <l>And what would now be thought a ſtrange deſigne,</l>
                  <l>To build a Houſe, was then to undermine.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="67" facs="tcp:170736:40"/>People liv'd under ground, and happy dwellers</l>
                  <l>Whoſe loftieſt habitations were all Cellars:</l>
                  <l>Thoſe Primitive times were innocent, for then</l>
                  <l>Man, who turn'd after Fox, but made his Den.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But, ſee a ſail of—trim and fine,</l>
                  <l>To court the rich <hi>Infanta</hi> of the Mine;</l>
                  <l>Hundreds of bold <hi>Leanders</hi> do confront,</l>
                  <l>For this lov'd <hi>Hero,</hi> the rough <hi>Helleſpont,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>'Tis an Armado Royal does engage</l>
                  <l>For ſome new <hi>Hellen</hi> with this equipage;</l>
                  <l>Prepar'd too, ſhould we their Addreſſes bar,</l>
                  <l>To force their Miſtreſs, with a ten years War:</l>
                  <l>But that our Mine's a common good, a joy</l>
                  <l>Made not to mine, but enrich our <hi>Troy.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But oh! theſe bring it with, 'em and conſpire</l>
                  <l>To pawn that Idol for our Smoake and Fire.</l>
                  <l>Silver's but Ballaſt, this they bring on ſhore,</l>
                  <l>That they may treaſure up our better Ore.</l>
                  <l>For this they venture Rocks and Storms, defie</l>
                  <l>All the extremity of Sea and Sky.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="68" facs="tcp:170736:41"/>For the glad purchaſe of this precious Mold,</l>
                  <l>Cowards dare Pyrates, Miſers part with Gold.</l>
                  <l>Hence is it, when the doubtful Ship ſets forth,</l>
                  <l>The Naving-needle ſtill directs her North:</l>
                  <l>And Natures ſecret wonder to atteſt</l>
                  <l>Our India's worth, diſcards both Eaſt and Weſt</l>
                  <l>For <hi>Tyne;</hi> nor only Fire commends this Spring,</l>
                  <l>A Coal-pit is a Mine of every thing.</l>
                  <l>We ſink a Jack-of-All-trades ſhop, and ſound</l>
                  <l>An Inverſe Burſe, an Exchange under ground.</l>
                  <l>This <hi>Proteus</hi>-earth converts to what you'l ha't,</l>
                  <l>Now you may wear't to Silk, now turn't to Plate:</l>
                  <l>And, what's a Metamorphoſis more dear,</l>
                  <l>Diſſolve it, and 'twill turn to <hi>London</hi>-Beer.</l>
                  <l>And whatſoe're that gaudy City boaſts,</l>
                  <l>Each Month does drive to our attractive Coaſts;</l>
                  <l>We ſhall exhauſt their Chamber, and devour</l>
                  <l>Their Treaſures at <hi>Guild-ball,</hi> and Mint i'th' <hi>Tower.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Our Stayth's their Mortgag'd Streets will ſoon divide,</l>
                  <l>Blazon their <hi>Cornhil-ſtella,</hi> ſhare <hi>Cheap-ſide.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="69" facs="tcp:170736:41"/>Thus ſhall our Coal-pits charity and pity,</l>
                  <l>At diſtance undermine and fire the City.</l>
                  <l>Should we exact, they'd pawn their Wives, and treat</l>
                  <l>To ſwoop thoſe Coolers for our ſoveraign heat.</l>
                  <l>'Bove kiſſes and embraces fire controuls;</l>
                  <l>No <hi>Venus</hi> heightens like a peck of Coals.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Medea</hi> was the Drug of ſome old Sire;</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Aeſon</hi>'s Bath a luſty Sea-coal-fire.</l>
                  <l>Chimneys are old mens Miſtreſſes, their ſins</l>
                  <l>A modern dalliance with their meazled ſhins.</l>
                  <l>To all Defects a Coal-pit gives a Cure;</l>
                  <l>Gives Youth to Age, and Raiment to the Poor.</l>
                  <l>Pride firſt wore Cloathes, Nature diſdains Attire;</l>
                  <l>She made us Naked, 'cauſe ſhe gave us Fire.</l>
                  <l>Full Wharffs are Ward-robes, and the Taylors charm</l>
                  <l>Belongs to th'Collier, he muſt keep us warm.</l>
                  <l>The quilted Alderman in all's Array,</l>
                  <l>Finds but cold comfort in a Summers-day;</l>
                  <l>Girt, wrapt, and muffled, yet with all this ſtir</l>
                  <l>Scarce warm, when ſmother'd in his drouſie Fur;</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="70" facs="tcp:170736:42"/>Nor proof againſt keen Winters batteries,</l>
                  <l>Should he himſelf wear all's own Liveries;</l>
                  <l>But Chil-blains under Silver-ſpurs bewails,</l>
                  <l>And in embroyder'd buskins blows his nails.</l>
                  <l>Rich Medows and full Crops are elſewhere found;</l>
                  <l>We can reap Harveſts from our barren ground.</l>
                  <l>The bald parch'd Hills that circumſcribe our <hi>Tyne,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Are no leſs pregnant in our happy Mine.</l>
                  <l>Their unfledg'd tops ſo well content our palats,</l>
                  <l>We envy none their Noſegays and their Sallets.</l>
                  <l>A gay rank Soyl, like a young Gallant goes,</l>
                  <l>And ſpends it ſelf, that it may wear fine Clothes;</l>
                  <l>Whilſt all its worth is to its back confin'd,</l>
                  <l>Ours wears plain out-ſide, but is richly lin'd.</l>
                  <l>Winter's above, 'tis Summer underneath,</l>
                  <l>A truſty Morglay in a ruſty ſheath.</l>
                  <l>As precious Sables ſometimes enterlace</l>
                  <l>A wretched Serge, or Grograin Caſſock caſe:</l>
                  <l>Rocks own no Spring, are pregnant with no Showers,</l>
                  <l>Criſtals and Gems are there inſtead of Flowers.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="71" facs="tcp:170736:42"/>Inſtead of Roſes, Beds of Rubies ſet,</l>
                  <l>And Emeralds recompence the Violet.</l>
                  <l>Dame Nature, not like other Madams, wears,</l>
                  <l>Though ſhe is bare, Pearls in her Eyes and Ears.</l>
                  <l>What though our Fields preſent a naked ſight?</l>
                  <l>A Paradice ſhould be an <hi>Adamite.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The Northern Lad his bonny Laſs throws down,</l>
                  <l>And gives her a black Bag for a green Gown.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>TO THE DUTCHESS OF <hi>CLEAVELAND.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>AS Sea-men ſhipwrackt on ſome happy ſhore,</l>
                  <l>Diſcover Wealth in Lands unknown before;</l>
                  <l>And what their Art had labour'd for in vain,</l>
                  <l>By their misfortunes happily obtain:</l>
                  <l>So my much-envy'd Muſe by Storms long toſt,</l>
                  <l>Is caſt upon your Hoſpitable Coaſt;</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="72" facs="tcp:170736:43"/>And finds more favour by her ill ſucceſs,</l>
                  <l>Than ſhe could hope for by her happineſs.</l>
                  <l>Once <hi>Cato</hi>'s Virtues did the Gods oppoſe,</l>
                  <l>When they the Victor, he the Vanquiſh'd choſe:</l>
                  <l>But you have done what <hi>Cato</hi> could not do,</l>
                  <l>To chuſe the Vanquiſh'd, and reſtore him too.</l>
                  <l>Let others ſtill triumph, and gain their cauſe</l>
                  <l>By their deſerts, or by the Worlds applauſe;</l>
                  <l>Let Merit Crowns, and Juſtice Laurels give,</l>
                  <l>But let me Happy by your Pity live.</l>
                  <l>True Poets empty Praiſe and Fame deſpiſe;</l>
                  <l>Fame is the Trumpet, but your Smiles the Prize.</l>
                  <l>You ſit above, and ſee vain men below</l>
                  <l>Contend for what you only can beſtow:</l>
                  <l>But thoſe great Actions others do by chance,</l>
                  <l>Are, like your Beauty, your Inheritance.</l>
                  <l>So great a Soul, ſuch ſweetneſs joyn'd in One,</l>
                  <l>Could only ſpring from Noble <hi>Grandiſon;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>You, like the Stars, not by reflexion bright,</l>
                  <l>Are born to your own Heav'n, and your own Light:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="73" facs="tcp:170736:43"/>Like them are good, but from a Nobler Cauſe,</l>
                  <l>From your own Knowledg, not from Natures Laws.</l>
                  <l>Your pow'r you uſe but for your own defence,</l>
                  <l>To guard your own, or others Innocence.</l>
                  <l>Your Foes are ſuch as they, not you, have made;</l>
                  <l>And Virtue may repel, though not invade.</l>
                  <l>Such courage did the Ancient <hi>Hero</hi>'s ſhow,</l>
                  <l>Who, when they might prevent, did wait the blow;</l>
                  <l>With that aſſurance, as they meant to ſay,</l>
                  <l>We will o'recome, but ſcorn the ſafeſt way.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Well may I reſt ſecure in your great Fate,</l>
                  <l>And dare my Stars to be unfortunate.</l>
                  <l>What further fear of danger can there be?</l>
                  <l>Beauty, that caſtives all things, ſets me free.</l>
                  <l>Poſterity would judge by my ſucceſs,</l>
                  <l>I had the Grecian Poets happineſs,</l>
                  <l>Who waving Plots, found out a better way;</l>
                  <l>Some God deſcended and preſerv'd the Play.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>When firſt the Triumphs of your Sex were ſung</l>
                  <l>By thoſe old Poets, Beauty was but young;</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="74" facs="tcp:170736:44"/>And few admir'd her native red and white,</l>
                  <l>Till Poets dreſt her up to charm the ſight.</l>
                  <l>So Beauty took on truſt, and did engage</l>
                  <l>For ſums of praiſes, till ſhe came of age:</l>
                  <l>But this vaſt growing Debt of Poeſie,</l>
                  <l>You, Madam, juſtly have diſcharg'd to me,</l>
                  <l>When your applauſe and favour did infuſe</l>
                  <l>New life to my condemn'd and dying Muſe;</l>
                  <l>Which, that the World as well as you may ſee,</l>
                  <l>Let theſe rude Verſes your Acquittance be.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Receiv'd in full this preſent day and year,</l>
                  <l>One ſoveraign ſmile from Beauties general Heir.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:170736:44"/>
               <head>To a Fooliſh Fair One.</head>
               <l>'TIs true, we all confeſs you fair,</l>
               <l>The red and white well plac'd;</l>
               <l>You have an eye beyond compare,</l>
               <l>A delicate ſmall waſte;</l>
               <l>That leads to ſuch delight as is</l>
               <l>Unſpeakable, like after-bliſs.</l>
               <l>A skin ſo pure, as new-faln ſnow</l>
               <l>For ſorrow melts away,</l>
               <l>Becauſe ſubdu'd in whiteneſs ſo;</l>
               <l>And ſoft as— what to ſay</l>
               <l>Compariſon limps far behind</l>
               <l>Your matchleſs body in my mind.</l>
               <l>But what's all this to purpoſe ſaid?</l>
               <l>As much as nothing yet;</l>
               <l>Shew me the Jewel here that's laid</l>
               <l>Up in this Cabinet.</l>
               <l>I'm for the kernel; and the ſhell,</l>
               <l>Though ne're ſo ſmooth, take he that will.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:170736:45"/>If peeviſhneſs, or proud diſdain</l>
               <l>Become a Noble Breſt,</l>
               <l>Ask any of <hi>Diana</hi>'s Train,</l>
               <l>Or Abbeſs of the reſt:</l>
               <l>And ſhe'l reſolve you, fooliſh Pride</l>
               <l>Ne're dwelt where Wiſdom does abide.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Fading BEAUTY.</head>
               <l>TAke Time, my Dear, e're Time takes wing;</l>
               <l>Beauty knows no ſecond Spring:</l>
               <l>Marble Pillars, Tombs of Braſs,</l>
               <l>Time breaks down, much more this Glaſs;</l>
               <l>Then e're that Tyrant Time beſpeak it,</l>
               <l>Let's drink healths in't firſt, then break it.</l>
               <l>At Twenty five in Womens eyes</l>
               <l>Beauty does fade, at Thirty dyes.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:170736:45"/>
               <head>To A Full Grown BEAUTY.</head>
               <lg n="1">
                  <head>I.</head>
                  <l>O Tarry, let me banquet on</l>
                  <l>Thoſe Cherries dropping-ripe on thee;</l>
                  <l>Too ſoon, alas, they will be gon,</l>
                  <l>And a cold Palſie ſhake the Tree.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="2">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <l>No Fawn, nor yet out-lying Deer,</l>
                  <l>Grazes within this Ivory Pale;</l>
                  <l>Yet what now likes, will loathe the ear,</l>
                  <l>And run into an old Wives Tale.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="3">
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <l>Thoſe Arms of <hi>York</hi> and <hi>Lancaſter</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>United in thy beauteous Cheek,</l>
                  <l>E're long will fall agen to War;</l>
                  <l>For Roſes then, where ſhall we ſeek?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="4">
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:170736:46"/>
                  <head>IV.</head>
                  <l>Thoſe heav'nly Lights which ſhine ſo clear,</l>
                  <l>As makes the days bright Eye to wink,</l>
                  <l>Muſt ſuffer ſtrange Eclipſes here,</l>
                  <l>And in their ſockets faintly ſink.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="5">
                  <head>V.</head>
                  <l>Thoſe pretty Balls of Panting ſnow,</l>
                  <l>That circle in the Milky way,</l>
                  <l>Shall two looſe hanging Udders grow,</l>
                  <l>And all your glories thus decay.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="6">
                  <head>VI.</head>
                  <l>Then be not fondly nice to ſpare</l>
                  <l>What unthrift time will lewdly ſpend;</l>
                  <l>Keep open houſe, and let me ſhare;</l>
                  <l>What freely came, as freely lend.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="7">
                  <head>VII.</head>
                  <l>E're Beauty breaks up houſe, and heart,</l>
                  <l>Prove hoſpitably kind, impart.</l>
                  <l>What Fools are they that lead their life in care,</l>
                  <l>To leave rich ſurfeits for a thankleſs Heir!</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:170736:46"/>
               <head>The ENJOYMENT.</head>
               <lg n="1">
                  <head>I.</head>
                  <l>FAr from the ſtately Edifice,</l>
                  <l>Where Princes dwell, and Lords reſort;</l>
                  <l>Weary of ſeeing in the Court</l>
                  <l>So much conſtraint and Artifice,</l>
                  <l>At home I liv'd in liberty,</l>
                  <l>Though my Heart did impriſon'd lye</l>
                  <l>Within my deareſt <hi>Silvia</hi>'s Breſt:</l>
                  <l>Nor fearing in her Love th'inconſtancy of Fate,</l>
                  <l>I led the ſweeteſt life for reſt,</l>
                  <l>That ever ſcap'd the Snares of Envy, Grief, or Hate.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="2">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <l>My Senſes kept intelligence</l>
                  <l>With my Deſires in equal meaſures,</l>
                  <l>And ſought me out a thouſand pleaſures</l>
                  <l>With a moſt faithful diligence.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="80" facs="tcp:170736:47"/>Each one my Fortune did admire,</l>
                  <l>To bleſs me Heaven did conſpire;</l>
                  <l>To make me happy, every Star</l>
                  <l>Caſt down ſo mild an influence on all my actions,</l>
                  <l>No oppoſition e're did bar</l>
                  <l>Me from enjoying to the full all my affections.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="3">
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <l>Thus was my ſtate incomparable,</l>
                  <l>So was my Miſtreſs, and my Love;</l>
                  <l>All others joyes I ſoar'd above</l>
                  <l>So high, that they ſeem'd miſerable.</l>
                  <l>I was a Lover much belov'd,</l>
                  <l>And 'midſt the frequent joy I prov'd</l>
                  <l>No bitterneſs was intermix'd;</l>
                  <l>But whilſt thereon I fed, the more that I enjoy'd,</l>
                  <l>The more my appetite was fix'd</l>
                  <l>To taſte agen, and yet my ſenſe was never cloy'd.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="4">
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:170736:47"/>
                  <head>IV.</head>
                  <l>Under our Climate Nature ſhows</l>
                  <l>Her Beauties naked to each eye,</l>
                  <l>Glutting the Light enchantingly</l>
                  <l>With the choice Objects ſhe beſtows.</l>
                  <l>Upon the Flowers we glittering ſpie</l>
                  <l>Tears, or rather Pearls to lie,</l>
                  <l>Dropt from the Cheeks of fair <hi>Auror';</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Wherewith ſhe to whom <hi>Zephirus</hi> makes Vows and Pray'rs,</l>
                  <l>And whom the blithe Spring does adore,</l>
                  <l>Does beautifie each Morn her Neck and Curled hair.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="5">
                  <head>V.</head>
                  <l>There 'mongſt the Smiles and the Careſſes,</l>
                  <l>The little frolick God inſpir'd,</l>
                  <l>Danc'd on th'enamel'd Graſs till tir'd</l>
                  <l>With his ſweet Miſtreſſes, the Graces.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="82" facs="tcp:170736:48"/>And ſtill when he deſir'd to Kiſs,</l>
                  <l>He came to reſt himſelf, Oh Bliſs!</l>
                  <l>Betwixt my <hi>Silvia</hi>'s ſnowy Breſts;</l>
                  <l>Whence he created thouſand new and freſh delights,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe Charms no Language can expreſs;</l>
                  <l>For every moment Life or Death was in their mights.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="6">
                  <head>VI.</head>
                  <l>Sometimes we ſaw a Satyr come,</l>
                  <l>Who ſitting in an Oaks freſh ſhade,</l>
                  <l>Upon his Pipe complaints then made</l>
                  <l>Of Love, and its ſweet Martyrdome.</l>
                  <l>Then walk'd we to a Grove apart,</l>
                  <l>Wherein the Sun no beam could dart,</l>
                  <l>To find out Solitarineſs.</l>
                  <l>And finding peaceful Reſt, with ſolitude there ſporting,</l>
                  <l>We baniſh'd all unquietneſs,</l>
                  <l>Leſt that might have diſturb'd our pretty harmleſs courting.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="7">
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:170736:48"/>
                  <head>VII.</head>
                  <l>There under a ſtraight Mirtle-tree,</l>
                  <l>(Which Lovers holy do eſteem)</l>
                  <l>Where grav'd by <hi>Venus</hi> hand had been</l>
                  <l>Her Trophies, and Loves Myſtery:</l>
                  <l>Moſt ſolemn Vows betwixt us paſt,</l>
                  <l>That our bright Flame ſhould ever laſt;</l>
                  <l>Nor ſhould its Ardour weaker grow.</l>
                  <l>Then offering up thoſe Oathes to our Victorious King,</l>
                  <l>We wrote them on the Bark below;</l>
                  <l>But they were deeper printed on our heart within.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="8">
                  <head>VIII.</head>
                  <l>Sometimes a little doubt I feign'd,</l>
                  <l>And in her Ear thus whiſpred I,</l>
                  <l>(Only to ſound her conſtancy)</l>
                  <l>Is your Love free, or elſe conſtrain'd?</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="84" facs="tcp:170736:49"/>Then keeping ſilence for a ſpace,</l>
                  <l>I ſigh'd, and with a mournful face</l>
                  <l>Proceeded thus with Lovers Art:</l>
                  <l>Shall I e're dare to hope? Oh heavenly Miracle!</l>
                  <l>To be as truly in your Heart</l>
                  <l>As in your Eyes, where I behold my ſelf ſo well.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="9">
                  <head>IX.</head>
                  <l>She mov'd with this, would anſwer me,</l>
                  <l>(Accuſing firſt my want of Faith)</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Lyſis,</hi> a place thy Image hath</l>
                  <l>Deeper than in my Eye can be:</l>
                  <l>I'le take thy ſelf to judge it here,</l>
                  <l>You know it cannot be ſo neer,</l>
                  <l>Since it appears ſo little, —Well,</l>
                  <l>Believe then, by reflected Lines thou doeſt it ſee</l>
                  <l>Grav'd on my heart, where it does dwell,</l>
                  <l>Thorow my eyes, as under Chryſtals pictures be.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="10">
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:170736:49"/>
                  <head>X.</head>
                  <l>At this reply, my raviſht ſpirits</l>
                  <l>Being rapt into a huge content,</l>
                  <l>I did implore her quick conſent</l>
                  <l>Unto more amorous delights.</l>
                  <l>And thus to make our conteſt ſhort,</l>
                  <l>I tempted her to that ſweet ſport</l>
                  <l>Wherewith a Woman's ſeldom cloy'd:</l>
                  <l>Claſping her in the heat, that great deſire provokes</l>
                  <l>(She yielding then to be enjoy'd)</l>
                  <l>Cloſer then amorous Vines embrace the ſturdy Oaks.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="11">
                  <head>XI.</head>
                  <l>Then on her melting Lips half cloſed</l>
                  <l>I tippled, kiſſing night and day</l>
                  <l>A health unto our Love alway,</l>
                  <l>Sipping that Cup whoſe brim was Roſted:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="86" facs="tcp:170736:50"/>My Shepherdeſs, as free as I,</l>
                  <l>Pledging thoſe healths moſt greedily,</l>
                  <l>Was o'recome with the ſame exceſs;</l>
                  <l>When having laviſhly thus ſpent our Amorous ſtore,</l>
                  <l>Our drooping Countenance did expreſs,</l>
                  <l>Thorow our languiſh'd looks, that we could do no more.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="12">
                  <head>XII.</head>
                  <l>Yet our deſires reſuming courage,</l>
                  <l>When our endeavors weakeſt grew,</l>
                  <l>Exercis'd many ways anew</l>
                  <l>Loves Game, for which each ſenſe did forage;</l>
                  <l>That ſweet bewitching paſſion</l>
                  <l>Led us with ſo much ardor on,</l>
                  <l>And all our motions were ſo hurl'd,</l>
                  <l>That who at that ſame time in <hi>Cypria</hi>'s Grove had ſeen us,</l>
                  <l>Would ſure have judg'd, that all the World</l>
                  <l>Had been the Wager of ſo fierce a Fight between us.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="13">
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:170736:50"/>
                  <head>XIII.</head>
                  <l>In this enjoyment ne'retheleſs</l>
                  <l>We ſcorn'd the World, and did content us</l>
                  <l>With thoſe only Joyes Love lent us,</l>
                  <l>Whilſt my ſtretcht Body hers did preſs.</l>
                  <l>A thouſand times of this more glad,</l>
                  <l>Then if both <hi>Indies</hi> we had had;</l>
                  <l>We wanted nothing thoſe ſhort hours:</l>
                  <l>'Twas not our wiſh, a Crown or Kingdom for to have;</l>
                  <l>We envy'd not Riches or Powers;</l>
                  <l>T'enjoy thoſe Pleaſures ſtill, was all that we did crave.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="14">
                  <head>XIV.</head>
                  <l>But oh! what Pen's enough laſcivious,</l>
                  <l>Were it pluckt from a Sparrows wing,</l>
                  <l>For to deſcribe ſo ſweet a thing</l>
                  <l>As theſe ſo oft enjoyments with us?</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="88" facs="tcp:170736:51"/>Never (though with Cloathes unlaced,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Venus</hi> her dear Love embraced)</l>
                  <l>Were ſuch various Sports invented:</l>
                  <l>Nor ere did Love, and's <hi>Pſyche</hi> fair with him,</l>
                  <l>Taſte ſuch delights, were ſo contented</l>
                  <l>As were our raviſht Souls, with this enticing Sin.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="15">
                  <head>XV.</head>
                  <l>The Tongue being o'th' party too,</l>
                  <l>When a cloſe Kiſs beſieg'd it, ſtraight</l>
                  <l>On the Lips borders it would wait,</l>
                  <l>And ſometimes forth in ſallies go:</l>
                  <l>The Enemy when its ſtroakes did come,</l>
                  <l>Found it ſo ſweet a Martyrdome,</l>
                  <l>That it did welcome each atteint;</l>
                  <l>Whilſt thouſand Smacks and Sighs at the ſame time ſerv'd there</l>
                  <l>For Songs of Victory; without plaints</l>
                  <l>Both vanquiſht and the Victor equally contented were.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="16">
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:170736:51"/>
                  <head>XVI.</head>
                  <l>One day cloſe by a murmuring Spring</l>
                  <l>Of liquid Silver purifi'd,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe wandring winding Stream did glide</l>
                  <l>Towards the Sea, and ran therein;</l>
                  <l>My Lute did ſpeak the ſofteſt ſtrain</l>
                  <l>Fingers could make, to entertain</l>
                  <l>My Fancy with; but then anon</l>
                  <l>I made the Strings break forth in a more vigorous ſound,</l>
                  <l>Which mov'd the very Rocks whereon</l>
                  <l>The luſty ſprightly Goats did often skip and bound.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="17">
                  <head>XVII.</head>
                  <l>Birds by the Muſick drawn in numbers,</l>
                  <l>Stretch'd forth their pretty necks to hear,</l>
                  <l>Panting as if they raviſh'd were,</l>
                  <l>Alike o'recome with joy and wonder.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="90" facs="tcp:170736:52"/>The Beaſts we every where did ſee</l>
                  <l>Gazing at us on bended knee;</l>
                  <l>Charm'd into ſilence all things were,</l>
                  <l>Whilſt from an aged Oak, inſpir'd with our content,</l>
                  <l>Theſe words diſtinctly we did hear,</l>
                  <l>Which in a pleaſing tone to us were ſent.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="18">
                  <head>XVIII.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Orpheus</hi> from <hi>Rhadamanthe</hi>'s ſight,</l>
                  <l>Hath now redeem'd from Hell again</l>
                  <l>(Spight of its Flames, and Fates ſtrong Chain)</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Euridice</hi> to heavenly Light.</l>
                  <l>That moſt unparallell'd Pair in Love,</l>
                  <l>Are once more now rejoyn'd above;</l>
                  <l>Twice parted againſt boths deſires,</l>
                  <l>His Head in which the Gods ſuch rare Gifts have enclos'd,</l>
                  <l>Nor his ſo much admired Lyre,</l>
                  <l>To the Waves mercy then it ſeems were not expos'd.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:170736:52"/>
               <head>A Land-Voyage in <hi>Ireland.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>AFter a Break-faſt, the laſt Sundays Eve,</l>
                  <l>By the Sun's Riſe, the <hi>Blarney</hi> we did leave;</l>
                  <l>Who at his getting up ſo ſmil'd and laught,</l>
                  <l>As if he'd drink the Clouds for's Mornings-draught.</l>
                  <l>But yet, alas, we had not gone a League,</l>
                  <l>When the falſe Weather turn'd directly <hi>Teige;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And the Wind too unkindly turned South,</l>
                  <l>And blew i'th' Teeth of thoſe had ſome, i'th' Mouth</l>
                  <l>Of thoſe had none, ſo that <hi>Betty</hi> th'unfair,</l>
                  <l>Spight of all wants, had ſuffer'd, if then there.</l>
                  <l>The Rain pour'd down ſo faſt, 'twas too well known</l>
                  <l>The Clouds were then not troubled with the Stone.</l>
                  <l>This did ſo greatly raiſe a little Brook,</l>
                  <l>That we did fear our way we had miſtook;</l>
                  <l>For 'twas ſo deep, that a Ship might have then</l>
                  <l>Floated, tho' laden with Committee-men.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="92" facs="tcp:170736:53"/>Which danger, when we found, we did begin</l>
                  <l>To wiſh each Hand and Foot had been a Fin.</l>
                  <l>At length by Land and Water we got o're,</l>
                  <l>And had no ſooner reacht the Pagan-ſhore,</l>
                  <l>But a bold <hi>Teige,</hi> e're I could look about,</l>
                  <l>Swore for to wet my inſide as my out.</l>
                  <l>With that he brought a Flagon, but ſo greaſie,</l>
                  <l>That had my Boots been half ſo much, with eaſe I</l>
                  <l>The Water had kept out, which I did fear</l>
                  <l>Much leſs than to let in his ſmaller Beer:</l>
                  <l>Beer, of which many ill things might be ſed,</l>
                  <l>Were't not unfit to ſpeak ill of the Dead.</l>
                  <l>Yet thus much of it I dare boldly ſay,</l>
                  <l>Though weak, it quickly drove us all away.</l>
                  <l>But that, you'll ſay, was not much for its Fame,</l>
                  <l>Since that the Water had neer done the ſame.</l>
                  <l>Having my potion drunk, I held it fit</l>
                  <l>To pay, though drinking I had paid for it:</l>
                  <l>Perhaps the Entertainer thought the ſame:</l>
                  <l>For, when but Money only I did name,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="93" facs="tcp:170736:53"/>He took't ſo ill, that clearly I do think,</l>
                  <l>Nothing could be worſe taken but his Drink.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Our Hoſt, at length, a little ſatisfi'd,</l>
                  <l>Yet more than we, our Beaſts we did beſtride,</l>
                  <l>And ſwitch and ſpur, a foot-pace rid away,</l>
                  <l>Unto the place where Captain <hi>Ruddock</hi> lay:</l>
                  <l>But wet ſo Cap-a-pee, that where we ſtood,</l>
                  <l>We almoſt there did raiſe a ſecond Flood;</l>
                  <l>Which made the half-drown'd Garriſon deſire</l>
                  <l>That we this marching Deluge would retire;</l>
                  <l>Nay, ſome of them ſtuck not to ſay aloud,</l>
                  <l>We were not Men, but a diſſolving Cloud.</l>
                  <l>Such were our Droppings, that if they had bin</l>
                  <l>Tears of Repentance, they had Drown'd our Sin.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Our half-becalmed Steeds we then did laſh on,</l>
                  <l>Till at the length we came to <hi>Bally-Glaſhon;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But ſome, as I thought, went with an ill will on,</l>
                  <l>Tho' that the <hi>Quarters</hi> were of Captain <hi>Dillon.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But there my watry Friends grew quickly merry,</l>
                  <l>Finding their Foord there turn'd into a Ferry;</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="94" facs="tcp:170736:54"/>Hoping that I no further would have gon,</l>
                  <l>But ended there our Navigation.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I ſcorn'd ſo poor a thought, and therefore got</l>
                  <l>A reeling <hi>Charon</hi> to a reeling <hi>Cott.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>It was a Miracle we were not ſunk,</l>
                  <l>Since that the Boat and Boat-man both were drunk.</l>
                  <l>Had but the firſt as full of Liquor bin</l>
                  <l>As the laſt was, nought could have made it ſwim.</l>
                  <l>That Axiom we did then experiment,</l>
                  <l>That nothing's weighty in its Element;</l>
                  <l>Elſe we had there miſcarried without doubt,</l>
                  <l>By <hi>Charon</hi>'s wet within, and ours without.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But of <hi>George Dillon,</hi> three Steeds I did borrow,</l>
                  <l>Which I made bold the Water to ſwim thorow.</l>
                  <l>Our Train we left there, and thoſe three that went-on,</l>
                  <l>Were I, my Servant <hi>Gibbs,</hi> and <hi>Maurice Fenton.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>So lean thoſe Gennets were, that I their ribs</l>
                  <l>Could ſee as plainly as I could ſee <hi>Gibbs:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, to ſpeak true, the beſt Beaſt that we were-on,</l>
                  <l>Was, both by Sire and Dam, a downright <hi>Garron.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="95" facs="tcp:170736:54"/>As for their mettle, you muſt think it rare,</l>
                  <l>When nought about them but their hair did ſtare.</l>
                  <l>Their out-ſide, tho 'twere harſh, yet ſure they be</l>
                  <l>The civil'ſt Creatures I did ever ſee;</l>
                  <l>For, without lying it might well be ſed,</l>
                  <l>To every thing they bow'd both knee and head;</l>
                  <l>Chiefly my own, which made me ſtrongly fear</l>
                  <l>I then did ride on an Idolater;</l>
                  <l>At leaſt, if it be lawful ſo to ſay</l>
                  <l>Of one who unto ſtones doth kneel and pray.</l>
                  <l>And when he ſtumbled, you might then as ſoon</l>
                  <l>Have hindred Fare, as him from falling down.</l>
                  <l>But yet ſo wanton, that between each ſpit</l>
                  <l>And ſtride, he ever inceſt would commit.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Maurice</hi> his Steed oft put him into fright</l>
                  <l>Of juſtly loſing the Name of <hi>White Knight.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The Horſe too that my Man was mounted on,</l>
                  <l>Was by his Maſter called <hi>Choridon.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which gallant Name did coſt the poor Jade dear,</l>
                  <l>It made him both <hi>Gibbs</hi> and the Cloak-bag bear;</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="96" facs="tcp:170736:55"/>Which forc'd the proud <hi>Getulian</hi> ſo to puff,</l>
                  <l>That we at firſt did think he took't in ſnuff.</l>
                  <l>And therefore for to right him I was minded,</l>
                  <l>Which doing, I ſoon found him broken-winded:</l>
                  <l>And that he ſhew'd too in ſo high a form,</l>
                  <l>I wondred, croſſing <hi>Styx,</hi> he rais'd no ſtorm.</l>
                  <l>This happy truth as ſoon as I did find,</l>
                  <l>I voted <hi>Gibbs</hi> ſtill for to ride behind;</l>
                  <l>Which tho I had not, here 'tis to be noted,</l>
                  <l>The Beaſt himſelf had done what I had voted:</l>
                  <l>So that when Mettle did in our Steeds fail,</l>
                  <l>That want was help'd by an obliging Gale.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But now I end, leſt ſome might truly ſay,</l>
                  <l>The Story is as tedious as the Way.</l>
                  <l>At length, with hazard both of Life and Lim,</l>
                  <l>By Candle-light <hi>Macroome</hi> we entred in;</l>
                  <l>So dirty, that even as much Rain agen</l>
                  <l>Could with much difficulty make us Clean.</l>
                  <l>Our Horſes too, as thoſe that ſaw them ſay,</l>
                  <l>Appear'd like moving Statues made of Clay;</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="97" facs="tcp:170736:55"/>And tho alive, did ſeem the ſelf-ſame Earth,</l>
                  <l>From whence at firſt they did derive their Birth.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>We were no ſooner lighted, but we there</l>
                  <l>Did offer up many a Curſe and Pray'r:</l>
                  <l>The firſt, a greater ſure we could not give,</l>
                  <l>Was, That our Horſes as they were might live;</l>
                  <l>And the laſt was, They might be rid by thoſe</l>
                  <l>Who were our Private and the Publick Foes.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>To A Fair MISTRESS.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Madam,</salute>
               </opener>
               <lg>
                  <l>TO praiſe you to your face, I think</l>
                  <l>As groſs a kindneſs as to ſprinkle Ink</l>
                  <l>Inſtead of thoſe Black-patches Ladies wear</l>
                  <l>As Foyls, to ſet their Beauties off more rare.</l>
                  <l>Troth, I muſt tell you plain, to climb the Skies</l>
                  <l>You muſt excuſe me for a caſt of Eyes;</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="98" facs="tcp:170736:56"/>And having put yours out, in eithers Grave</l>
                  <l>T'inocculate a Star, 'tis wondrous brave,</l>
                  <l>I muſt confeſs, and ſpeaks a Giant Muſe,</l>
                  <l>Such monſtrous high ſimilitudes to uſe;</l>
                  <l>They cannot chuſe but a rare Beauty make,</l>
                  <l>When all the Bulls and Bears th'ave brought to ſtake;</l>
                  <l>That ſay her Name were <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſula,</hi> I'le wager,</l>
                  <l>In place of <hi>Minor,</hi> ſhe ſhall be the <hi>Major;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Her Cheeks the <hi>Milkie-way,</hi> where the whole Team</l>
                  <l>Of Deities eat Strawberries and Cream;</l>
                  <l>And when they call for healths, young <hi>Hebe</hi> trips,</l>
                  <l>And taps full Bowls of Nectar from her Lips:</l>
                  <l>The very Dimple of her Chin is ſo,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cupid</hi> there hides his Quiver and his Bow:</l>
                  <l>And, if this Dimple be ſo wide, I trow,</l>
                  <l>(Hark in your Ear) What think ye's that below?</l>
                  <l>Fool that I was, 'tis eaſie to beguile</l>
                  <l>The ignorant, I ſee; for all this while</l>
                  <l>Until I heard her thighs white Marble were,</l>
                  <l>I thought the man brought <hi>ſtones,</hi> not found them there.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="99" facs="tcp:170736:56"/>By that time to the Moon ſhe's full compar'd,</l>
                  <l>With Atoms powdred, with the Sun-beams hair'd,</l>
                  <l>Tooth'd like an Elephant, at leaſt like Pearl;</l>
                  <l>Will ſhe not ſeem a luſty ſtrapping Girl?</l>
                  <l>Her Legs, the Poles on which this Heaven ſtands;</l>
                  <l>Sure ſhe wears pretty Shoes, ſmall Gloves on Hands.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But let each Lover chuſe what he ſees good,</l>
                  <l>I love a Miſtreſs made of fleſh and blood;</l>
                  <l>And of thoſe mortal Beauties, to ſay true,</l>
                  <l>I love none more, 'cauſe none more fair than you.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Againſt WOMEN.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>WOman at firſt intended was, no doubt,</l>
                  <l>To pleaſe and comfort man; not took to pout</l>
                  <l>At every trifle, till in ſome fond paſſion,</l>
                  <l>Man over-kind alter'd her true Creation,</l>
                  <l>As Kings did Popes; to whom the Proverb well</l>
                  <l>Extends, That give an inch, they'll take an ell.</l>
                  <l>And ſince experience ſhews each Dame one,</l>
                  <l>In ſtate, as teeming, fain would be Pope <hi>Jone;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="100" facs="tcp:170736:57"/>So learn the garb of Pride; ſpeaks ſharp, is cruel,</l>
                  <l>Obſerves no mean, no reaſon: Here's a Jewel</l>
                  <l>To truſt indeed! a pretty piece of Folly</l>
                  <l>To cope with in a ſerious Melancholy:</l>
                  <l>Whoſe Will's her Law, whoſe Terms allow we muſt,</l>
                  <l>(And ſhort Vacations too;) whoſe Love's meer Luſt;</l>
                  <l>Grant all ſhe asks, or talks, be ſure to pleaſe,</l>
                  <l>Or elſe be ſure to live in little eaſe.</l>
                  <l>Where once her ſpleen's againſt, no Egge ſo ill</l>
                  <l>Can Malice lay, but ſhe ſits brooding ſtill;</l>
                  <l>Her Tears as full of Treaſon as her Smiles,</l>
                  <l>And both intrapping like the Crocodiles.</l>
                  <l>Not a poor minute certain, juſt like one</l>
                  <l>Plays faſt and looſe; now here, now <hi>preſto,</hi> gone.</l>
                  <l>Who carries Tales, brings Sweet-meats; it's no matter,</l>
                  <l>To pleaſe her, what they ſorge, or how they flatter.</l>
                  <l>Nor cares ſhe how ſhe makes her Lover ſad;</l>
                  <l>But croſs her in the leaſt, ſhe runs ſtark mad.</l>
                  <l>When ſhe's trickt up in all her gay attire,</l>
                  <l>Leſs cauſe ſee I to love her than admire.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="101" facs="tcp:170736:57"/>Take her undreſt, and all her Trinkets out,</l>
                  <l>There's a ſweet Prize to keep ſuch coyl about!</l>
                  <l>One ſets 'em well together, he that ſwears,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Woomen and Dogs ſet all the World by th'Ears.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O for ſome other way to Propagate,</l>
                  <l>Than this accurſed cauſe of all Debate!</l>
                  <l>Where noble Friendſhip muſt be quite caſhier'd,</l>
                  <l>If ſhe ſit down believ'd, or but once heard;</l>
                  <l>And if her pet's not ſerv'd i'th'nick, far leſs</l>
                  <l>Undecent noiſe makes the robb'd Lioneſs.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Eve</hi> by the Serpent was beguil'd; my mind</l>
                  <l>Gives me, that Serpent entred all the Kind.</l>
                  <l>Had that firſt Anabaptiſt herd (I mean</l>
                  <l>Thoſe Swine that Satan waſht away ſo clean)</l>
                  <l>Been left, and every Female that made head,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>That's all the Sex but ten, dipt in their ſtead.</l>
                  <l>(Perhaps too, thoſe are tranſmigrated now,</l>
                  <l>Since each foul grunting Quean's baptized <hi>Sow</hi>)</l>
                  <l>O what a jolly Bone-fire had the Prince</l>
                  <l>Of Darkneſs made! How many Men ſav'd ſince?</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="102" facs="tcp:170736:58"/>Leſs flames by thouſands Earth to Hell had ſent,</l>
                  <l>As ſmall fires ſerve where the chief fuel's ſpent.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But are not Women helps? yes, nought ſo ſure,</l>
                  <l>Helps to undo men, if they'll it endure.</l>
                  <l>If thou ſit ſtill, and little have to ſay,</l>
                  <l>She'll help thee to diſcourſe, but her own way;</l>
                  <l>So full of groſs impertinence, at beſt;</l>
                  <l>Imagine when ſhe's froward, what's the reſt?</l>
                  <l>Has't an Eſtate? and would'ſt improve it well?</l>
                  <l>Leave it to her, ſhe'll help thee pawn or ſell,</l>
                  <l>To buy this Toy, that other coſtly faſhion,</l>
                  <l>Or elſe diſgrace thee with a Miſers paſſion.</l>
                  <l>Art thou well ſtockt with ſtrength, and health to friend it?</l>
                  <l>She'll help thee to a paſtime that ſhall ſpend it.</l>
                  <l>If Women then ſuch helps oft prove to be,</l>
                  <l>Let them help who they will, pray God help me.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:170736:58"/>
               <head>ANSWER In Defence of WOMEN.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>WHat wild diſtemper has poſſeſt thy brain,</l>
                  <l>Harſh Satyriſt, in ſuch uncomely ſtrain</l>
                  <l>To wound that heavenly Race, the joys of men,</l>
                  <l>All at one ſtroke aſſaſſin'd by thy Pen?</l>
                  <l>As if a general defection had</l>
                  <l>Seiz'd all the Sex, becauſe a few prove bad:</l>
                  <l>Or that on Church, 'cauſe ſome Fanaticks fall,</l>
                  <l>It needs muſt follow w'are Fanaticks all.</l>
                  <l>Recant, or fly, for lo the ſacred Band</l>
                  <l>Of Wit and Valour Feminine's at hand.</l>
                  <l>The twice-ſteel'd Goddeſs claps her Armor on,</l>
                  <l>And leads the van againſt thee, ſo that none</l>
                  <l>Of all the Muſes, or a Grace, combin'd</l>
                  <l>Thus altogether, now dare ſtay behind.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="104" facs="tcp:170736:59"/>Who weeping ſate by their own Fountain dri'd</l>
                  <l>Up in this ſun-burnt age, born to deride</l>
                  <l>Their ſacred influence; and when they ſing</l>
                  <l>With unwaſht hands, pollute the Virgin-ſpring.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Led by the Grecian <hi>Hero</hi>'s, they diſplay</l>
                  <l>For Colours the Chaſte Wife of <hi>Ithaca,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>With a full Troop attending; and that Dame</l>
                  <l>Whoſe coſtly Faith keeps freſh the breath of Fame;</l>
                  <l>Who built her Lord a Tomb with wondrous Art,</l>
                  <l>Yet not ſo rich, as that about her heart.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The fam'd <hi>Lucretia,</hi> and <hi>Paulina</hi>'s try'd</l>
                  <l>Endear'd affection, poize the <hi>Roman</hi> ſide:</l>
                  <l>On whom the Veſtals wait with holy fire,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe flames not burn, but only warm deſire;</l>
                  <l>With Regiments well fill'd of youthful years,</l>
                  <l>That Muſter paſs under thoſe Brigadeers.</l>
                  <l>But what remoter Times and parts have known,</l>
                  <l>We find at home contracted in our own.</l>
                  <l>Take one for all the reſt, whoſe worth unſtain'd,</l>
                  <l>Makes perfect truth what perhaps Poets fain'd;</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="105" facs="tcp:170736:59"/>That ſhould falſe tongues lick all my hopes away,</l>
                  <l>And in her or'e-caſt Eye benight my Day;</l>
                  <l>As who can ſcape thoſe Ear-wigs, if ſo near</l>
                  <l>They wriggle in, as to aſſault the Ear?</l>
                  <l>(And it is eaſie, where they'l be ſo vicious,</l>
                  <l>T'intrap an honeſt meaning unſuſpicious)</l>
                  <l>I'd wear her frowns for favors, and would deem</l>
                  <l>Them marks of caution, not of diſeſteem.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Go, light thy Taper at yon' Ladies Eyes,</l>
                  <l>Where Day doth ſeem to break, the Sun to riſe</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>On equal <hi>Hymen,</hi> who ne're minds the parts,</l>
                  <l>But gets a trick to joyn Eſtates, not Hearts;</l>
                  <l>He that does Marry thinks not ſure he takes</l>
                  <l>An Angel into his embrace, nor makes</l>
                  <l>A Deity of Duſt, and ſuch are we;</l>
                  <l>If there be fleſh and blood, ſome faults will be.</l>
                  <l>Tho the mad Pens of Lovers Idolize,</l>
                  <l>Yet in cold blood, try'd Husbands are more wiſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Wedlock's the Lifes grand Sallet, if its Oyl'd,</l>
                  <l>Without ſome Vineger the taſte is ſpoyl'd.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="106" facs="tcp:170736:60"/>He that damns all but for the faults of ſome,</l>
                  <l>Deſtroys his Orchard for a rotten Plum,</l>
                  <l>Or Crab-tree-ſtock, when a diſcreeter Fate</l>
                  <l>Would graft upon it, or inoculate.</l>
                  <l>Like to the Sot, ſo out of love with Print,</l>
                  <l>He burns his Book for ſome Errata's in't.</l>
                  <l>'Tis a meer humor this, which ſpent, you then</l>
                  <l>Cry Women up, as faſt as down the Men;</l>
                  <l>Though 'tis unnatural, becauſe confeſt</l>
                  <l>Even by themſelves, that down they'r at the beſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>All that but looks like fair, great, good on Earth,</l>
                  <l>Takes from a Female its firſt riſe and birth.</l>
                  <l>Talk of high thoughts, who will Ambition prize,</l>
                  <l>Does any thing make Man like Woman riſe?</l>
                  <l>Can there be Love without her, or true Wealth?</l>
                  <l>She's his beſt Mine, beſt Doctor for his Health,</l>
                  <l>His all in all; in her embraces ſtands</l>
                  <l>That little World, the greater which commands.</l>
                  <l>She's ſuch a Mint as Coyns him Young agen,</l>
                  <l>And makes his Stamp paſs currant amongſt Men.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="107" facs="tcp:170736:60"/>Talks ſhe at random, as you here define?</l>
                  <l>'Tis but as wiſeſt Men will do ſometime;</l>
                  <l>To me thoſe ſweet Diverſions freſh appear,</l>
                  <l>A running Banquet, after heavy chear.</l>
                  <l>Man helpleſs were without her help indeed;</l>
                  <l>The Worlds great Spirit would be loſt, and Seed.</l>
                  <l>Then helpleſs let him be doth ſo require;</l>
                  <l>So help me God, as I ſuch help deſire.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Fooliſh NICETY.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>I Hate a ſullen Miſtreſs, of ſuch tumor,</l>
                  <l>Put in a Jeſt, it puts her out of Humor;</l>
                  <l>Fondly miſtakes each paſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                        <desc>••…</desc>
                     </gap> word I ſay,</l>
                  <l>Takes pet, as Tinder fire, then fools away</l>
                  <l>Her ſelf in Childiſh anger: if ſhe ſpeaks,</l>
                  <l>At beſt, when beſt ſhe's pleas'd, poor thing it breaks</l>
                  <l>Into ſuch woful phraſe, doth ſo disburſe</l>
                  <l>Odd ends of Gold and Silver in diſcourſe,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="108" facs="tcp:170736:61"/>That, as I live, 'tis much againſt my will,</l>
                  <l>For her own credit, ſhe's not ſilent ſtill:</l>
                  <l>Better ſhut up in ſilence, tho ſhe go</l>
                  <l>For Proud, than open to her overthrow.</l>
                  <l>What's a fair Woman ſimply? Shall I tell ye?</l>
                  <l>A Box of Mummy, or of warmer Jelly;</l>
                  <l>Which for a taſte, or ſo, may currant paſs,</l>
                  <l>But not to make a meal on: Where's that Aſs</l>
                  <l>A piece of Snout-fair ignorance would marry?</l>
                  <l>Sooner I'd hew a Miſtreſs from the Quarry</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pigmalion</hi> once carv'd out; I'd ſooner go</l>
                  <l>On pilgrimage to <hi>Mecha,</hi> and there throw</l>
                  <l>My Eyes on burning Bricks, till all about</l>
                  <l>The Nerves and Sinews crackt, their Lamps leapt out,</l>
                  <l>Than fix on ſuch a Wife; take this from me,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>There's nought ſo fulſome as a Fooliſh She.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:170736:61"/>
               <head>On The Victory over the <hi>Spaniards</hi> in the <hi>Bay</hi> of <hi>Sancta Crux,</hi> in the Iſland of <hi>Teneriffe.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>NOw does <hi>Spains</hi> Fleet her ſpacious wings unfold,</l>
                  <l>Leaves the New World, and haſtens to the Old;</l>
                  <l>But tho the Wind were fair, they ſlowly ſwom,</l>
                  <l>Fraighted with active guilt, and guilt to come;</l>
                  <l>For this Rich load, of which ſo proud they are,</l>
                  <l>Was rais'd by Tyranny, and rais'd for War.</l>
                  <l>Ev'ry capacious Galleons Womb was fill'd</l>
                  <l>With what the Womb of wealthy Kingdoms yield:</l>
                  <l>The New Worlds wounded Intrails they had tore</l>
                  <l>For Wealth, wherewith to wound the Old one more.</l>
                  <l>Wealth, which all others Avarice might cloy,</l>
                  <l>But yet in them caus'd as much Fear as Joy.</l>
                  <l>For now upon the Main themſelves they ſaw,</l>
                  <l>That boundleſs Empire where we give the Law.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="110" facs="tcp:170736:62"/>Of Winds and Waters rage they fearful be,</l>
                  <l>But much more fearful th'Engliſh Flags to ſee.</l>
                  <l>Day, that to thoſe who ſail upon the Deep</l>
                  <l>More wiſht for, and more welcome is then Sleep,</l>
                  <l>They dreaded to behold, leſt the Sun's Light</l>
                  <l>With our dread Streamers ſhould ſalute their ſight.</l>
                  <l>In thickeſt Darkneſs they would chuſe to ſteer,</l>
                  <l>So that ſuch Darkneſs might ſuppreſs their fear.</l>
                  <l>At length theirs vaniſhes, and Fortune ſmiles,</l>
                  <l>For they behold the ſweet <hi>Canary</hi>-Iſles;</l>
                  <l>One of which doubtleſs is by Nature bleſt</l>
                  <l>Above both Worlds, ſince 'tis above the reſt.</l>
                  <l>For leſt ſome Gloomineſs might ſtain her Sky,</l>
                  <l>Trees there the Duty of the Clouds ſupply.</l>
                  <l>O Noble Truſt, which Heav'n on this Iſle pours,</l>
                  <l>Fertile to be, yet never need her ſhowrs!</l>
                  <l>A happy People, which at once do gain</l>
                  <l>The Benefits without the Ills of Rain!</l>
                  <l>Both Health and Profit Fate cannot deny,</l>
                  <l>Where ſtill the Earth is moiſt, the Air ſtill dry.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="111" facs="tcp:170736:62"/>There jarring Elements no diſcord know,</l>
                  <l>Fewel and Rain together kindly grow;</l>
                  <l>And Coolneſs there with Heat does never fight,</l>
                  <l>This only Rules by Day, and that by Night.</l>
                  <l>There the indulgent Soyl the rich Grape breeds,</l>
                  <l>Which of the Gods the fancied Drink exceeds:</l>
                  <l>They ſtill do yield, ſuch is their precious mold,</l>
                  <l>All that is good, and are not curs'd with Gold,</l>
                  <l>With fatal Gold: for where e're it does grow,</l>
                  <l>Neither the Soyl nor People quiet know;</l>
                  <l>Which troubles men to raiſe it while 'tis Ore,</l>
                  <l>And when 'tis rais'd, it troubles them much more.</l>
                  <l>Ah! why was thither brought that cauſe of war</l>
                  <l>Kinde Nature had from thence remov'd ſo far?</l>
                  <l>In vain doth ſhe thoſe Iſlands free from ill,</l>
                  <l>If Fortune can make guilty what ſhe will.</l>
                  <l>'But whilſt I draw the Scene where we ere long</l>
                  <l>'Again may conquer, this is left unſung.</l>
                  <l>For <hi>Sancta Crux,</hi> the glad Fleet takes her way,</l>
                  <l>And ſafely there caſts Anchor in the Bay.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="112" facs="tcp:170736:63"/>Never ſo many with one Joyful Cry,</l>
                  <l>That place ſaluted where they all muſt die.</l>
                  <l>Deluded men! Fate with you did but ſport;</l>
                  <l>You ſcapt the Sea, to periſh in the Port;</l>
                  <l>'Twas more for <hi>England</hi>'s Fame you ſhould Die there,</l>
                  <l>Where you had moſt of Strength, and leaſt of Fear.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Peek's proud height the <hi>Spaniards</hi> do admire,</l>
                  <l>Yet in their Breſts carry a Pride much higher:</l>
                  <l>Only to this vaſt Hill a pow'r is giv'n,</l>
                  <l>At once both to inhabit Earth and Heav'n;</l>
                  <l>But this ſtupendious proſpect did not near</l>
                  <l>Make them admire ſo much as they did fear.</l>
                  <l>For here they met with News which did produce</l>
                  <l>A Grief above the Cure of Grapes beſt Juyce;</l>
                  <l>They learn'd, with terror, that nor Summers heat,</l>
                  <l>Nor Winters ſtorms could make our Fleet retreat.</l>
                  <l>To fight againſt ſuch Foes was vain, they knew,</l>
                  <l>Which did the rage of Elements ſubdue;</l>
                  <l>Who on the Ocean, that does horror give</l>
                  <l>To all beſides, Triumphantly do live.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="113" facs="tcp:170736:63"/>With haſte they therefore all their Gallions moar,</l>
                  <l>And flank with Cannon from the neighboring ſhore;</l>
                  <l>Forts, Lines, and Sconces, all the Bay along</l>
                  <l>They build, and act all that can make them ſtrong.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Fond men! who know not whilſt ſuch Works they raiſe,</l>
                  <l>They only Labour to exalt our Praiſe.</l>
                  <l>Yet they by reſtleſs Toyls became at length</l>
                  <l>So proud and confident of their made ſtrength,</l>
                  <l>That they with joy their boaſting General heard,</l>
                  <l>Wiſht then for that Aſſault they lately fear'd.</l>
                  <l>His wiſh he hath, for now undaunted <hi>Blake,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>With winged ſpeed, for <hi>Sancta Crux</hi> does make;</l>
                  <l>For our Renown his Conquering Fleet does ride</l>
                  <l>O're Seas as vaſt as is the <hi>Spaniards</hi> Pride;</l>
                  <l>Whoſe Fleet and Trenches view'd, he ſoon did ſay,</l>
                  <l>We to their ſtrength are more oblig'd than they:</l>
                  <l>Were't not for that, they from their Fate would run,</l>
                  <l>And a third World ſeek out, our Arms to ſhun.</l>
                  <l>Thoſe Forts which there ſo high and ſtrong appear,</l>
                  <l>Do not ſo much ſuppreſs, as ſhew their Fear.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="114" facs="tcp:170736:64"/>Of ſpeedy Victory let no man doubt;</l>
                  <l>Our worſt work's paſt, now we have found them out.</l>
                  <l>Behold, their Navie does at Anchor lie;</l>
                  <l>And they are ours, for now they cannot flie!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This ſaid, the whole Fleet gave it their applauſe,</l>
                  <l>And all aſſum'd his courage for the Cauſe;</l>
                  <l>That Bay they enter, which unto them owes</l>
                  <l>The nobleſt Wreathes that Victory beſtows.</l>
                  <l>Bold <hi>Stayner</hi> leads: this Fleet's deſign'd by Fate</l>
                  <l>To give him Lawrel, as the laſt did Plate.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The thundring Cannon now begins the Fight,</l>
                  <l>And, though it be at Noon, creates a Night;</l>
                  <l>The air was ſoon, after the Fight begun,</l>
                  <l>Far more inflam'd by it, than by the Sun.</l>
                  <l>Never ſo burning was that Climate known;</l>
                  <l>War turn'd the <hi>Temperate,</hi> to the <hi>Torrid</hi> Zone.</l>
                  <l>Fate had thoſe Fleets juſt between both worlds brought</l>
                  <l>Who fight as if for both thoſe worlds they fought.</l>
                  <l>Thouſands of ways, thouſands of men there die;</l>
                  <l>Some ſhips there ſunk, ſome blown up in the skie.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="115" facs="tcp:170736:64"/>Nature ne'r made Cedars ſo high aſpire</l>
                  <l>As Oaks did there, urg'd by the active fire,</l>
                  <l>Which by quick Powders force ſo high was ſent,</l>
                  <l>That it return'd to its own element.</l>
                  <l>Torn limbs ſome Leagues into the Iſland flie,</l>
                  <l>Whilſt others lower in the Sea do lie:</l>
                  <l>Scarce ſouls from bodies ſo far ſever'd are</l>
                  <l>By death, as bodies there were by fierce War.</l>
                  <l>Th' all-ſeeing Sun ne'r gaz'd on ſuch a ſight;</l>
                  <l>Two dreadful Navies there at Anchor fight;</l>
                  <l>And neither have or power or will to flie;</l>
                  <l>There one muſt Conquer, or there both muſt die.</l>
                  <l>Far different motions yet engag'd them thus;</l>
                  <l>Neceſſity did them, but Choice did us:</l>
                  <l>A Choice which did the higheſt worth expreſs,</l>
                  <l>And was attended by as high Succeſs.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>England</hi>'s reſiſtleſs <hi>Genius</hi> there did raign,</l>
                  <l>By which we Lawrels reapt even on the Main.</l>
                  <l>So proſperous Stars, though abſent to the ſenſe,</l>
                  <l>Bleſs thoſe they ſhine for, by their influence.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="116" facs="tcp:170736:65"/>Our Cannon now tears ev'ry Ship and Sconce,</l>
                  <l>And o're two Elements triumphs at once.</l>
                  <l>Their Gallions ſunk, their Wealth the Sea does fill,</l>
                  <l>The only place where it can cauſe no ill.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Ah! would thoſe Treaſures which both <hi>Indies</hi> have</l>
                  <l>Were buried in as large and deep a Grave!</l>
                  <l>Wars chief ſupport with them would buried be,</l>
                  <l>And the Land owe her Peace unto the Sea.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Ages to come our Conquering Arms will bleſs,</l>
                  <l>They there deſtroy'd what had deſtroy'd their Peace;</l>
                  <l>And in one War the preſent Age may boaſt,</l>
                  <l>The certain Seeds of many Wars are loſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>All the Foes Ships deſtroy'd by Sea or Fire,</l>
                  <l>Victorious <hi>Blake</hi> does from the <hi>Bay</hi> retire;</l>
                  <l>His Siege of <hi>Spain</hi> he then again purſues,</l>
                  <l>And there firſt brings of his Succeſs the News.</l>
                  <l>(The ſaddeſt News which e're to <hi>Spain</hi> was brought,</l>
                  <l>Their rich Fleet ſunk, and ours with Laurel fraught.)</l>
                  <l>"Whilſt Fame in every place her Triumph blows,</l>
                  <l>"And tells the World how much to us it ows.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:170736:65" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>Upon the ſight of a Fair Ladies Breech, diſcovered at her being turned over in a Coach. <hi>Tranſlated out of French.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg n="1">
                  <head>I.</head>
                  <l>I Yield, I yield, fair <hi>Phillis,</hi> now</l>
                  <l>My Heart muſt to your Empire bow;</l>
                  <l>I am your Pris'ner, for I find</l>
                  <l>Y'ave Conquered both my Will and Reaſon;</l>
                  <l>But you ſurprized me behind,</l>
                  <l>And is not that a kind of Treaſon?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="2">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <l>Againſt your Eyes I plac'd a Guard,</l>
                  <l>And kept my Freedom, though 'twere hard</l>
                  <l>Withſtanding that moſt tempting Face;</l>
                  <l>When finding I again drew near,</l>
                  <l>You chang'd your Ambuſh, and did place</l>
                  <l>Your murthering <hi>Cupids</hi> in your Rear.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="3">
                  <pb n="118" facs="tcp:170736:66"/>
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <l>At this firſt fight my heart did yield;</l>
                  <l>For every glance did pierce my Shield:</l>
                  <l>The faireſt Face it did outbid.</l>
                  <l>Could I reſiſt my Fate, or Stars,</l>
                  <l>When this ſlye enemy lay hid</l>
                  <l>So cloſe, and took me unawares?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="4">
                  <head>IV.</head>
                  <l>It ſeiz'd me both with love and fear,</l>
                  <l>Seeing ſo many beauties there;</l>
                  <l>And brought me, fond fool, to that paſs,</l>
                  <l>That, <hi>Perſian</hi>-like, I ſtraight did run,</l>
                  <l>Seeing your white Breech on the graſs,</l>
                  <l>To adore that new-riſing Sun.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="5">
                  <head>V.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Phoebus</hi> was glad to veil his eyes,</l>
                  <l>Finding that greater luſtre riſe;</l>
                  <l>And thought to ſteal away ere night,</l>
                  <l>Thinking his beams were uſeleſs now:</l>
                  <l>Which he had done, but that the fight</l>
                  <l>Staid him, in hopes to kiſs it too.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="6">
                  <pb n="119" facs="tcp:170736:66"/>
                  <head>VI.</head>
                  <l>The Satyrs much enamour'd were,</l>
                  <l>Beholding all the Graces there;</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Zephyrus</hi> eſpying too</l>
                  <l>Some other Charms, ſo lik'd them, that</l>
                  <l>Deſpight of all <hi>Flora</hi> could do,</l>
                  <l>He often kiſs'd your You-know-what.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="7">
                  <head>VII.</head>
                  <l>The Roſe, the Flowers lovely Queen,</l>
                  <l>Droopt, when your freſher skin was ſeen:</l>
                  <l>Lilies lookt pale, and ſhed a tear:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Narciſſus</hi> was brought to that paſs,</l>
                  <l>He left his ſelf-lov'd-Shade, and there</l>
                  <l>Gaz'd in your brighter Looking-glaſs.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="8">
                  <head>VIII.</head>
                  <l>Nor is there ought on earth ſo fair,</l>
                  <l>No Face that's worthy its compare:</l>
                  <l>No Cheeks, no Lips, Eyes darting rays:</l>
                  <l>'Mongſt all thoſe Beauties, there's no grace</l>
                  <l>Nor Meen, but ſoon will looſe its praiſe,</l>
                  <l>When your Breech but appears i'th' place.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="9">
                  <pb n="120" facs="tcp:170736:67"/>
                  <head>IX.</head>
                  <l>'Tis true, I fear 't has ſome defects</l>
                  <l>Will trouble me in theſe reſpects:</l>
                  <l>For it is very coy and ſhye,</l>
                  <l>Harder than the white Rock to break;</l>
                  <l>Nor hath it either Ear or Eye,</l>
                  <l>And's very rarely heard to ſpeak.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="10">
                  <head>X.</head>
                  <l>But ſo I love it, that my Verſe</l>
                  <l>Shall to the World its praiſe rehearſe;</l>
                  <l>Whilſt dayly I will make reſort</l>
                  <l>To pay my homage to this Queen,</l>
                  <l>Who leaves behind her this report</l>
                  <l>Of th'ſweeteſt Beauty e're was ſeen.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="11">
                  <head>XI.</head>
                  <l>O hide it then from all but me,</l>
                  <l>For were't unvail'd ſtill, Gods would be</l>
                  <l>My Rivals, and deſcend anew;</l>
                  <l>Who (though they ſit on Stars above)</l>
                  <l>They ſit on meaner Thrones than you;</l>
                  <l>For your Breech is the Throne of Love.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="121" facs="tcp:170736:67"/>
               <head>Upon the intolerable Heat in the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter end of <hi>May</hi> and the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>June,</hi> 1665.</head>
               <lg n="1">
                  <head>I.</head>
                  <l>FIre, fire, fire, fire, the Bells all backward ring:</l>
                  <l>Haſte, haſte to every Well and Spring;</l>
                  <l>Let ev'ry Cock, and ev'ry Spout</l>
                  <l>With noiſe and fury ruſh like Winter-torrents out.</l>
                  <l>Pull from the Churches Walls the Buckets down;</l>
                  <l>Bring forth thoſe Engines that defend each Town;</l>
                  <l>Engines which now ſingly more uſeful are</l>
                  <l>Than all that <hi>Archimedes</hi> made for War.</l>
                  <l>Yet theſe cannot ſuffize, 'tis not one Town;</l>
                  <l>It is not <hi>Newport</hi> now alone</l>
                  <l>That's burnt, each City feels the ſame;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>England</hi>'s on fire, and all the Iſle does flame.</l>
                  <l>Riſe then kind Rivers from your low-ſunk Beds,</l>
                  <l>Lift up your curled Heads;</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="122" facs="tcp:170736:68"/>With raiſed waters quickly go,</l>
                  <l>And all the parched land in welcome haſte oreflow.</l>
                  <l>Let <hi>Trent</hi> and <hi>Medway</hi> meet,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Thames</hi> and <hi>Tweed</hi> each other greet,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Severn</hi> and <hi>Chane</hi> their ſtreams conjoyn,</l>
                  <l>And crooked <hi>Wye</hi> mix with the Northern <hi>Tyne:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>All this and more this Summers fire</l>
                  <l>Does for to quench its killing rage require.</l>
                  <l>All theſe too little be;</l>
                  <l>To quench us we muſt call the Sea;</l>
                  <l>And for this ſuccour we ſhall owe him more</l>
                  <l>Than all our traffick and defence before.</l>
                  <l>Return, you waves, and your old triumphs gain:</l>
                  <l>Behold, we wiſh a Deluge once again.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="2">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <l>In ſpight of what Philoſophers have prov'd,</l>
                  <l>We finde the Poles are mov'd:</l>
                  <l>Theſe <hi>England</hi> from its Northern climate turn,</l>
                  <l>Which now beneath the Line doth burn:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="123" facs="tcp:170736:68"/>This needs muſt be, or elſe the Sun</l>
                  <l>His wonted conſtant Stages has outrun</l>
                  <l>In <hi>May,</hi> the <hi>Lion</hi> reacht the <hi>Dog</hi> in <hi>June,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who madded with his heat too ſoon,</l>
                  <l>Does with great fury rage and bite,</l>
                  <l>And wreak on us below his more than uſual ſpight.</l>
                  <l>Is then the doated Sire of <hi>Phaeton</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Become a Boy again, and like his ſon,</l>
                  <l>The Fiery Chariot does miſguide,</l>
                  <l>And where his horſes hurry him does ride,</l>
                  <l>Whilſt that his hands grown feeble now with age,</l>
                  <l>Can guide no more their headſtrong rage?</l>
                  <l>Or elſe has <hi>Cupid,</hi> thus to ſhew</l>
                  <l>That ſtill he has the better Bow,</l>
                  <l>Shot to his heart again ſome hot deſire,</l>
                  <l>With ſome new <hi>Daphne</hi> ſet his breſt on fire?</l>
                  <l>Whom that in Verſe he may intreat,</l>
                  <l>He kindles too his own Poetick heat.</l>
                  <l>And thus this triple fire inflames the weather,</l>
                  <l>Whilſt he is burnt, and burns the world together.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="3">
                  <pb n="124" facs="tcp:170736:69"/>
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <l>Alas, Love kindles a more gentle flame,</l>
                  <l>From him ſuch diſmal Fires ne're came:</l>
                  <l>No, this is rage, and <hi>Phoebus</hi> angry is,</l>
                  <l>When his face ſhines ſo bright as this;</l>
                  <l>We now at length the Poets meaning know,</l>
                  <l>Who tell us of his Arrows and his Bow.</l>
                  <l>His Rays are thoſe ſharp Darts he threw</l>
                  <l>When he the Monſter <hi>Python</hi> ſlew;</l>
                  <l>With them the <hi>Grecian</hi> Camp with death he fill'd,</l>
                  <l>And more than all the <hi>Trojans</hi> kill'd.</l>
                  <l>No Armor 'gainſt theſe Darts is proof,</l>
                  <l>Nor hardeſt Iron, nor tougheſt Buff:</l>
                  <l>Such is their ſtrange inchanted Power found,</l>
                  <l>They moſt of all the Armed wound.</l>
                  <l>But yet ſubmiſſion neither cannot ſhield</l>
                  <l>Thoſe that caſt down their Arms and yield;</l>
                  <l>Relentleſs ſtill the Sun his Rage does keep,</l>
                  <l>Though not our Eyes alone, but all our Body weep.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="125" facs="tcp:170736:69"/>He is ſoftned ne're the more,</l>
                  <l>Though a Tear fall from every Pore;</l>
                  <l>His Temples and his Altars loſt,</l>
                  <l>Which had ſo much the Heathen coſt;</l>
                  <l>His Horſes and his Sacrifices gone,</l>
                  <l>He now revenges upon us alone.</l>
                  <l>All <hi>England</hi> one great Altar is,</l>
                  <l>Which ſhines and burns with ſacred Fire of his:</l>
                  <l>Nor will ten thouſand Herds alone ſuffice,</l>
                  <l>But all its People too are made one Sacrifice.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="4">
                  <head>IV.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Apollo</hi> thus, who did at <hi>Delphos</hi> yield,</l>
                  <l>Again retakes the Field;</l>
                  <l>And our Religion, his victorious Foe,</l>
                  <l>Endeavors yet to overthrow:</l>
                  <l>So far alas he gets the day</l>
                  <l>By force of many a perſecuting Ray,</l>
                  <l>That whoſoe're to Church does come,</l>
                  <l>Endures a Martyrdome.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="126" facs="tcp:170736:70"/>Each Choriſt in the Quire</l>
                  <l>Sings Anthems like the Martyrs in the fire:</l>
                  <l>Each is his own and neighbours Funeral-pile,</l>
                  <l>On which all do themſelves and others broyl.</l>
                  <l>Did but their inward zeal, and outward heat,</l>
                  <l>Make but a Blaze ſo great,</l>
                  <l>The Churches Tapers might then ſhew their light,</l>
                  <l>Through their tranſparent Lanthorns bright:</l>
                  <l>For there are few whoſe bloud</l>
                  <l>Swells with a youthful floud;</l>
                  <l>Few at their hot devotions, or none,</l>
                  <l>Have ought but Linen on:</l>
                  <l>The Surplice is no more</l>
                  <l>A Veſt of Ceremony, as before.</l>
                  <l>Our neereſt Garments do for it make way,</l>
                  <l>And yeild it is more uſeful far than they.</l>
                  <l>The rigid Nonconformiſt who could bear,</l>
                  <l>Ev'n when his rage and zeal at hotteſt were,</l>
                  <l>An heavie, thick, unweildy Cloak,</l>
                  <l>Would all his former railings ſtraight revoke,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="127" facs="tcp:170736:70"/>Felt he this heat here, nay forſake</l>
                  <l>His Cloak and Doublet, and the Surplice take.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="5">
                  <head>V.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Moloch,</hi> that monſtrous Coloſs, all of braſs,</l>
                  <l>Who God at once and Altar was,</l>
                  <l>Who many a ſacrificed Hebrew child</l>
                  <l>Within his red-hot glowing arms hath kill'd,</l>
                  <l>Scarce heretofore did thoſe</l>
                  <l>With crueller embraces cloſe,</l>
                  <l>Than our Gowns us, who with the Sun conſpire</l>
                  <l>To ſet our kindled bodies all on fire:</l>
                  <l>Hither thoſe Drums, here let thoſe Trumpets ſound,</l>
                  <l>Which then the cries of tortur'd infants drown'd;</l>
                  <l>We ſtraight ſhall roar out full</l>
                  <l>As loud as he who firſt hanſel'd his burning Bull.</l>
                  <l>Nor is our noiſe alone as great,</l>
                  <l>But that which cauſes it, our heat:</l>
                  <l>Off therefore goes the Gown,</l>
                  <l>We caſt our Doublets down;</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="128" facs="tcp:170736:71"/>Our looſned Breeches fall,</l>
                  <l>And to our Shirts we ſoon are ſtripped all.</l>
                  <l>Nor ſhould our Cloathes, though they ſhould be</l>
                  <l>Far finer than the <hi>French</hi> trim Beggery;</l>
                  <l>Though deckt with all the Jewels of the Eaſt,</l>
                  <l>With all the Gold and Pearls o'th' Weſt:</l>
                  <l>Although they ſhone more richly gay</l>
                  <l>Than the <hi>Mogul</hi>'s, upon his own Birth-day,</l>
                  <l>The great <hi>Mogul</hi>'s, who at his ears</l>
                  <l>The price of <hi>European</hi> Kingdoms wears;</l>
                  <l>Whoſe Daggers hilt does in its Gems diſplay</l>
                  <l>An <hi>Aſiatick</hi> Armies pay.</l>
                  <l>Although more Jewels ſhould our Garments hide,</l>
                  <l>They ſhould not tempt our pride</l>
                  <l>To keep us dreſt one moment there</l>
                  <l>Where all mankinde ſpectators were;</l>
                  <l>If to the Sun as we our Jewels turn,</l>
                  <l>Whilſt that he makes them ſhine, he makes us burn.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="6">
                  <pb n="129" facs="tcp:170736:71"/>
                  <head>VI.</head>
                  <l>Our Cloathes are off, yet every ſingle Shirt</l>
                  <l>Still burns as much, as much does hurt,</l>
                  <l>As that of <hi>Hercules,</hi> which heretofore</l>
                  <l>With <hi>Hydra</hi>'s poiſon ſtain'd, and <hi>Neſſus</hi> gore.</l>
                  <l>So both reveng'd, none but would chuſe</l>
                  <l>Ev'n all his bloud to loſe,</l>
                  <l>So that his wounds might be</l>
                  <l>But half ſo ſmarting to his enemy.</l>
                  <l>The eating threds his fleſh gat in,</l>
                  <l>His Shirt ſate cloſer than his Skin:</l>
                  <l>The ſpreading venome grew,</l>
                  <l>Through all his mighty limbs it in an inſtant flew.</l>
                  <l>Through every artery and vein</l>
                  <l>It bore an univerſal pain:</l>
                  <l>The Purple-rivers of his bloud</l>
                  <l>In vain the fire withſtood:</l>
                  <l>They boil themſelves, and feel the ſame;</l>
                  <l>Theſe ſtreams like thoſe of burnt <hi>Scamander</hi> flame.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="130" facs="tcp:170736:72"/>His very bones <hi>Alcides</hi> kindled felt;</l>
                  <l>He felt his marrow melt,</l>
                  <l>And therefore built his Funeral-pyre,</l>
                  <l>And ſoon to cool himſelf leapt in the gentler fire.</l>
                  <l>With ſuch a furious heat</l>
                  <l>Our Shirts too make us ſweat;</l>
                  <l>Which though no venome ſtain,</l>
                  <l>Than <hi>Hydra</hi>'s fertile ſtings they cauſe a greater pain.</l>
                  <l>Off therefore ſoon they go;</l>
                  <l>Down our laſt torments ſo</l>
                  <l>With them we think to grow:</l>
                  <l>But yet the ſtubborn heat does ſtill perplex,</l>
                  <l>Still our tir'd patience vex;</l>
                  <l>Some ſecret unſeen cover</l>
                  <l>Doth preſs and ſcald all over:</l>
                  <l>Something would yet be needs put off, and we</l>
                  <l>Than nakedneſs it ſelf would fain more naked be.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="7">
                  <head>VII.</head>
                  <l>But ſee! cool <hi>Charwel</hi> ſoftly by does glide;</l>
                  <l>There our bare skins we gladly hide:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="131" facs="tcp:170736:72"/>Could but thoſe Artiſts, who with skilful Preſs,</l>
                  <l>On Water'd Tabbie waves expreſs;</l>
                  <l>Could they ſome Stuff of real water make,</l>
                  <l>Their former trade they'd ſoon forſake;</l>
                  <l>No other garments would be ſought,</l>
                  <l>No other Stuff be bought:</l>
                  <l>Our native finer Cloath we ſhould not prize,</l>
                  <l>And, though deep dy'd in grain with Cocheneal, deſpiſe.</l>
                  <l>The Silks that haughty <hi>Naples</hi> brags,</l>
                  <l>Would be accounted rags;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Brocadoes,</hi> and rich Cloth of Gold,</l>
                  <l>No more to us by <hi>Genoa</hi> ſhould be ſold:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Chineſe</hi> and <hi>Indian</hi> Manufactures here</l>
                  <l>None then would wear,</l>
                  <l>Nor any elſe beſide,</l>
                  <l>That Merchants profit ſerve, or Courtiers pride.</l>
                  <l>For thoſe no Ship ſhould croſs the Seas,</l>
                  <l>When the next ſhore with better ſtuff would pleaſe.</l>
                  <l>But ſince no Virtuoſo's daring Wit</l>
                  <l>Hath ventur'd yet hot limbs to fit</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="132" facs="tcp:170736:73"/>With cooling Summer-ſuits of water made,</l>
                  <l>We cannot wait th'inventing of the Trade.</l>
                  <l>Art tedious is, and ſlow;</l>
                  <l>To Natures ready gifts we go;</l>
                  <l>Into th'inviting ſtream our ſelves in haſte we throw.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="8">
                  <head>VIII.</head>
                  <l>O what a raviſhing coolneſs now does glide</l>
                  <l>Into our veins from every ſide!</l>
                  <l>A gentle, freſh, reviving cold</l>
                  <l>Does all embold:</l>
                  <l>The wanton waves about us ſport,</l>
                  <l>And as we them, they us do court;</l>
                  <l>That ore our ſhoulders leaps, and this</l>
                  <l>Steals from our lips a ſudden kiſs:</l>
                  <l>And then as fearing to be ſpi'd,</l>
                  <l>As nimbly back does glide.</l>
                  <l>We ſwim, and ſtretch our arms out wide, to have</l>
                  <l>A full embrace of each beloved wave.</l>
                  <l>Nor does to kiſs or to embrace ſuffice</l>
                  <l>Our wide voluptuous avarice;</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="133" facs="tcp:170736:73"/>Our heads and all go down;</l>
                  <l>Our ſelves all ore we in our pleaſures drown.</l>
                  <l>Nor do we care</l>
                  <l>For the delay of neceſſary air:</l>
                  <l>Who would not change a moments breath</l>
                  <l>For th'extaſies of this ſhort pleaſing death?</l>
                  <l>The waves of <hi>Styx</hi> ne'r led</l>
                  <l>The pious dead</l>
                  <l>To an <hi>Elizium</hi> that could pleaſe</l>
                  <l>So much as now the breathleſs divers theſe.</l>
                  <l>All pleaſures and all riches that are known,</l>
                  <l>Their liquid coolneſs comprehends alone.</l>
                  <l>So much that he that would recount</l>
                  <l>How far earths wealth the waters doth ſurmount,</l>
                  <l>Need not ſpeak ought of rich <hi>Pactolus</hi> Strand,</l>
                  <l>Nor <hi>Tagus</hi> golden ſand;</l>
                  <l>Nor how the Eaſtern Pilgrims yearly go</l>
                  <l>Their Coyn in <hi>Ganges</hi> ſacred ſtream to throw.</l>
                  <l>He need not tell how in the Ocean lies</l>
                  <l>The wealth of diſappointed Treaſuries:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="134" facs="tcp:170736:74"/>The golden Wrecks which ev'ry year</l>
                  <l>Storms and tempeſts drowned there;</l>
                  <l>The Spaniſh Fleets on purpoſe caſt away,</l>
                  <l>Leſt they become the conquering <hi>Engliſh</hi> prey:</l>
                  <l>Theſe riches which from ſpoyl'd earth came,</l>
                  <l>He need not name,</l>
                  <l>Nor yet what are more precious far than theſe,</l>
                  <l>The native Pearls and Coral of the Seas:</l>
                  <l>More than all this may in one word be told;</l>
                  <l>Who doubts the waters price, who now but hears 'tis cold?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="9">
                  <head>IX.</head>
                  <l>Lovers do now no more</l>
                  <l>Thoſe ſparkling eyes by which they're burnt adore:</l>
                  <l>Their being like the Sun,</l>
                  <l>Now hatred draws, which former praiſes won.</l>
                  <l>The Water-nymphs alone now pleaſe,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Venus</hi> onely raigns within her native Seas.</l>
                  <l>All <hi>Peleus</hi> happie fortune praiſe,</l>
                  <l>Which him to <hi>Thetis</hi> happie bed did raiſe.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="135" facs="tcp:170736:74"/>To <hi>Thetis</hi> bed, that fair Sea-nymph, whoſe love</l>
                  <l>Was thought too great a happineſs for <hi>Jove;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Were ſhe now preſent here,</l>
                  <l>None to embrace her cloſe would fear,</l>
                  <l>Although, transform'd again, ſhe ſhould appear</l>
                  <l>A Lion, Tyger, Leopard, Bear,</l>
                  <l>Or any Monſter elſe like theſe,</l>
                  <l>Which Saylors fright upon her imitating Seas;</l>
                  <l>So that at laſt her ſelf again</l>
                  <l>A Water-nymph ſhe would remain.</l>
                  <l>The Ladies too, as much as they deſire</l>
                  <l>A vigorous youth, all heat, all fire,</l>
                  <l>Yet now perhaps would ſcarce approve</l>
                  <l>For a Gallant the mighty <hi>Jove,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>If ſuch as when to <hi>Semele</hi> he came,</l>
                  <l>Clad in lightning and in flame,</l>
                  <l>His love ſo fiercely burn'd,</l>
                  <l>That its own object it to aſhes turn'd,</l>
                  <l>Her flames aſcended to the skie,</l>
                  <l>Whither her too ambitious love did flie.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="136" facs="tcp:170736:75"/>A cooler Wooer now they love,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Neptune</hi> ſpight of Fate prefer to <hi>Jove.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Juno</hi> may ceaſe her uſual ſpight,</l>
                  <l>None may be jealous now but <hi>Amphitrite.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or if <hi>Jove</hi> chance to be</l>
                  <l>In love with ſome new <hi>Danaë,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>He muſt now orecome her Tower</l>
                  <l>Not with a golden, but a watry ſhower.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="10">
                  <head>X.</head>
                  <l>What then ſhall we to bounteous <hi>Charwel</hi> give</l>
                  <l>For all the pleaſures we receive?</l>
                  <l>Shall we a Graſſie Altar build</l>
                  <l>In the next fruitful field?</l>
                  <l>There ſacrifice a ready Ox or Cow</l>
                  <l>Which neither Yoke nor Milk-pail know;</l>
                  <l>A Goat, a Kid, a Ram,</l>
                  <l>Or many a tender Lamb;</l>
                  <l>And with their Conſecrated bloud</l>
                  <l>Augment his ſinking floud?</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="137" facs="tcp:170736:75"/>Shall we his Curled head,</l>
                  <l>Which now with Reeds is onely covered,</l>
                  <l>With all the flowry Garlands crown,</l>
                  <l>Which the great Garden of the Town</l>
                  <l>The Market ſhews, or Gardens yield</l>
                  <l>The Markets of the field?</l>
                  <l>Into his waters ſhall we pour forth wine,</l>
                  <l>The richeſt Juyce of the <hi>Canary</hi>-Vine;</l>
                  <l>And for the coolneſs of our kinde retreat,</l>
                  <l>Repay as kinds an heat?</l>
                  <l>No, none of theſe he loves;</l>
                  <l>Theſe ancient honours all he diſapproves.</l>
                  <l>He who ſo long ran on the <hi>Britiſh</hi> ſand,</l>
                  <l>So many hundred years a Chriſtian Land,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe waters unto Fonts convey'd,</l>
                  <l>So many Chriſtians have made;</l>
                  <l>In his own waves ſo far baptized is,</l>
                  <l>As to think it much amiſs</l>
                  <l>That we our ſelves again ſhould make</l>
                  <l>Idolaters and Pagans for his ſake.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="138" facs="tcp:170736:76"/>Nay, though himſelf were Heathen ſtill,</l>
                  <l>He would not ſuffer we ſhould kill</l>
                  <l>Thoſe beaſts for him for whom he has</l>
                  <l>So long provided Hay and Graſs:</l>
                  <l>To more ignoble Man he leaveth that,</l>
                  <l>Who thoſe he does intend for to devour makes fat.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="11">
                  <head>XI.</head>
                  <l>The Flowers his fertile waters bred,</l>
                  <l>Through the earths ſubtil chanel ſpread,</l>
                  <l>Since to himſelf ſo neer alli'd,</l>
                  <l>For his ſake to be cut he counts it Parricide.</l>
                  <l>As he the Drunkards Garden will not uſe,</l>
                  <l>So he his Wine too doth refuſe:</l>
                  <l>His Fiſhes lives he loves to ſpare,</l>
                  <l>Who but too oft intoxicated are;</l>
                  <l>Who in ſuch numbers die,</l>
                  <l>Their greedieſt Hoſt to ſatisfie,</l>
                  <l>And by their drunkenneſs his gluttony ſupply.</l>
                  <l>Since then he'll none of theſe receive,</l>
                  <l>Good wiſhes we can onely give.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="139" facs="tcp:170736:76"/>May therefore this exceſſive heat,</l>
                  <l>His enemy and ours, retreat:</l>
                  <l>May he not any where for dread</l>
                  <l>Of the hot Sun hide underneath his head,</l>
                  <l>Nor yet again let Winter-flouds confuſe</l>
                  <l>His courſe, whilſt in himſelf, himſelf he ſwoln may loſe:</l>
                  <l>But let a plenty clear and ſtill,</l>
                  <l>Brim-high his undiſturbed Chanel fill:</l>
                  <l>May none with Dams reſtrain his force,</l>
                  <l>Nor interrupt his courſe;</l>
                  <l>May none his Mother-ſtream divide,</l>
                  <l>Nor into petty Dykes his waters turn aſide:</l>
                  <l>May not his liquid ſtate</l>
                  <l>So periſh by unhappie Empires fate:</l>
                  <l>May no foul Sinks his clearneſs ſpoil,</l>
                  <l>No Common-ſhore his ſtream defile:</l>
                  <l>But let him chaſte and clear enter fair <hi>Iſis</hi> bed,</l>
                  <l>And Virgin-<hi>Thames</hi> himſelf a Virgin wed.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="12">
                  <pb n="140" facs="tcp:170736:77"/>
                  <head>XII.</head>
                  <l>May their innumerable Progenie</l>
                  <l>The Fiſhy <hi>Trent</hi> outvie;</l>
                  <l>Repleniſhed with theſe,</l>
                  <l>Let 'em creep ſoftly to the Seas,</l>
                  <l>Thorow rank Graſs, full Corn, and lofty Trees,</l>
                  <l>By wealthy Farms, and ſtately Palaces:</l>
                  <l>But ſtill be ſure that by the way</l>
                  <l>They both their homage pay,</l>
                  <l>Their daily tribute bring</l>
                  <l>To their whole elements great univerſal King,</l>
                  <l>In whoſe large Throne</l>
                  <l>We <hi>Jove</hi> and <hi>Neptune</hi> ſee conjoyn'd in one;</l>
                  <l>Tridents in one, Scepters in th'other hand,</l>
                  <l>Sway both the Sea and Land;</l>
                  <l>The Kingdoms Pilot, he the Navies King,</l>
                  <l>Both to a happie Port do bring:</l>
                  <l>Both with ſo skilful hands do ſteer,</l>
                  <l>Nor hidden Rocks, nor open Streams they fear.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="141" facs="tcp:170736:77"/>From his great Palace they may then go down,</l>
                  <l>And view that Ocean of a Town,</l>
                  <l>That Sea of wealth which does enfold</l>
                  <l>All the rich Rivers gold.</l>
                  <l>This they may coaſt too, ſince they know</l>
                  <l>She all to them does owe:</l>
                  <l>But yet deſcending with the Tyde,</l>
                  <l>They finde a cauſe of greater pride.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="13">
                  <head>XIII.</head>
                  <l>Theſe wiſhes we to <hi>Charwel</hi> owe</l>
                  <l>For the ſweet Cold that in his waves do flow.</l>
                  <l>But yet our pleaſures grow more great,</l>
                  <l>In that we round us ſtill perceive the vanquiſht heat:</l>
                  <l>Thence freſh delights ariſe,</l>
                  <l>That whilſt ſo neer us it doth tyrannize,</l>
                  <l>His force we laugh at and deſpiſe:</l>
                  <l>Still we midſt flaming ſwords enjoy our paradiſe.</l>
                  <l>Although a Furnace round us glow,</l>
                  <l>We ſtill are cool, like <hi>Aetna</hi>'s conſtant Snow;</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="142" facs="tcp:170736:78"/>That valiant Snow which does defeat</l>
                  <l>The neighb'ring power of all that Magazine of heat.</l>
                  <l>Whilſt not a Cloud does flatter in the skie,</l>
                  <l>Wells, Pools, and many Brooks be dry,</l>
                  <l>We to our lips ſtand up,</l>
                  <l>Like happie Sun-dew in our well-fill'd Cup,</l>
                  <l>That Jovial plant whoſe fate now all things wiſh,</l>
                  <l>Which ev'n at general draughts but laughs,</l>
                  <l>Whilſt in her brim-full nat'ral diſh</l>
                  <l>The unexhauſted <hi>Roſa Solis</hi> quaffs.</l>
                  <l>This <hi>Charwel</hi> ſtill whilſt deep, though faln, he flows,</l>
                  <l>On us alone beſtows.</l>
                  <l>The parched earth he ſuccour can't:</l>
                  <l>His neareſt Meadows do his preſence want;</l>
                  <l>Their wide deep cracks do gape in vain</l>
                  <l>For flouds and for delaying rain:</l>
                  <l>The earth does with a thouſand mouthes complain,</l>
                  <l>And heav'n of foul ingratitude accuſe,</l>
                  <l>That can quick aid refuſe;</l>
                  <l>Who though ſhe had receiv'd from her below</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="143" facs="tcp:170736:78"/>Her Rains exhal'd, her Hail, her Snow,</l>
                  <l>Doth yet he hold her Benefactreſs burn,</l>
                  <l>And not one ſingle ſhower, one ſingle drop return.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="14">
                  <head>XIV.</head>
                  <l>Now that the Earth their Nurſes breſts are dry,</l>
                  <l>The infant-Plants grow ſick and die;</l>
                  <l>Not one of all their mouthes, one luckie root</l>
                  <l>Cannot ſuck one poor drop into't.</l>
                  <l>Thus choakt and baniſht, in one place they have</l>
                  <l>A Cradle and a Grave:</l>
                  <l>The reſt do droop, and for the dead</l>
                  <l>Each ſeems to mourn, and hang his penſive head;</l>
                  <l>But none one dewie tear can ſhed;</l>
                  <l>That mournful rain,</l>
                  <l>Were't not to them as to ſad men in vain,</l>
                  <l>Thoſe tears would keep them all alive,</l>
                  <l>And ev'n the dead they weep for too revive.</l>
                  <l>But now their thirſty grief</l>
                  <l>Cannot that way procure its own relief;</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="144" facs="tcp:170736:79"/>Amaz'd they know not why,</l>
                  <l>For what grand crime they thus ſhould die.</l>
                  <l>What cauſleſs rage</l>
                  <l>Could thus engage</l>
                  <l>That civil God <hi>Apollo</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>His ſavage Grandſire <hi>Saturn</hi>'s crime to follow,</l>
                  <l>Who to ſecure his power,</l>
                  <l>All his own off-ſpring did devour?</l>
                  <l>Like Cruelty what makes <hi>Apollo</hi> uſe,</l>
                  <l>His power to loſe;</l>
                  <l>Whilſt thoſe ſame Plants for whoſe wiſe uſe old Fame</l>
                  <l>Did him the God of Phyſick name;</l>
                  <l>Thoſe Plants with which loſt health he did reſtore,</l>
                  <l>And from the jaws of death preys half devoured tore,</l>
                  <l>He makes declining from their vigour lie,</l>
                  <l>Themſelves on their ſick beds, and of one Fever die?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="15">
                  <head>XV.</head>
                  <l>Hence juſtly all the children of the Spring</l>
                  <l>The Sun their Tyrant count, and not their King.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="145" facs="tcp:170736:79"/>The proudeſt Flow'rs now hate the very light</l>
                  <l>That ſhews their beauties to our ſight:</l>
                  <l>The amorous Marigold that turns</l>
                  <l>To her dear Sun, he now not warms, but burns,</l>
                  <l>Weary of his import'nate ray,</l>
                  <l>Would ſpight of Love and Nature turn away.</l>
                  <l>Thoſe tender fruits that hardly bear</l>
                  <l>The ſharpneſs of our Northern air,</l>
                  <l>Whom the Sun yet could ne'r make ripe with all</l>
                  <l>His force, unleſs aſſiſted by a wall;</l>
                  <l>On the moſt ſhady bough,</l>
                  <l>Not ripe alone, but roaſted now.</l>
                  <l>Thoſe courteous Ladies whoſe kinde hands reprieve</l>
                  <l>The periſhing fruits, and give</l>
                  <l>By their obliging art a longer date</l>
                  <l>To their ſhort fate,</l>
                  <l>And ſo the Winter make and Spring</l>
                  <l>The Summers and the Autumns pleaſures bring,</l>
                  <l>Need now no more whilſt they deſire</l>
                  <l>Their fruit to keep, by the ſame fire</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="146" facs="tcp:170736:80"/>Their beauties loſe, nor to raiſe enmities</l>
                  <l>Betwixt our pleaſed taſtes, and our defrauded eyes,</l>
                  <l>Their Sweet-meats with due colours now to grace,</l>
                  <l>They need not ſpoil a better in their face:</l>
                  <l>Some ſugred water let their Gardners throw</l>
                  <l>On the ſcorcht trees, and ſo</l>
                  <l>The Fruits will turn to Sweet-meats as they grow:</l>
                  <l>The heat which all before did ſpoil,</l>
                  <l>Will them in that new Liquor boil.</l>
                  <l>So Cherries, Grapes, or Goosberries,</l>
                  <l>Plums, Apricocks, or any fruits they pleaſe,</l>
                  <l>Preſerved they may gather from the trees.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="16">
                  <head>XVI.</head>
                  <l>This ſcorched heat in Gardens raigns,</l>
                  <l>In ſpight of all the Gardners care and pains,</l>
                  <l>And all his Watring-pots poor counterfeited rains.</l>
                  <l>A fiercer fire burns up th' unwatred field,</l>
                  <l>Which had been better left until'd.</l>
                  <l>The piercing Sun-beams aged trunks invade,</l>
                  <l>Through all the numerous leaves that hide them in their ſhade.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="147" facs="tcp:170736:80"/>The Oak that grows on the moſt ſhady vale,</l>
                  <l>Would with her kindred in the Navie ſail;</l>
                  <l>And leſs would fear</l>
                  <l>Dutch Fire-ſhips there,</l>
                  <l>Than the Suns rays more formidable here:</l>
                  <l>There ready water would her flames ſurround,</l>
                  <l>But here ſhe burns upon the burning ground.</l>
                  <l>For fear of this, all without winde may ſhake,</l>
                  <l>And trembling Aſps excuſed quake:</l>
                  <l>Many already ſhew their griefs and fears</l>
                  <l>In copious gummy tears;</l>
                  <l>And well they may,</l>
                  <l>Since though ſtill green, and Lightning-proof, the Bay</l>
                  <l>Is almoſt ſcorcht by her own <hi>Phoebus</hi> ray.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="17">
                  <head>XVII.</head>
                  <l>But theſe effects of the Suns ſpight</l>
                  <l>Are all but light:</l>
                  <l>Worſe torments his malignant influence</l>
                  <l>Inflicts on them to whom unhappie ſenſe</l>
                  <l>Cruelly-bounteous Nature did diſpenſe:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="148" facs="tcp:170736:81"/>Their feeling like a Burning-glaſs,</l>
                  <l>Doubles the fiery rays, as through their skins they paſs.</l>
                  <l>Hence from each ecchoing Rock there does rebound</l>
                  <l>Tormented Cattels mournful ſound:</l>
                  <l>The faireſt and moſt healthful Cow</l>
                  <l>Would gladly live like that of <hi>Myron,</hi> now;</l>
                  <l>Since all our Herds of fire are quite as full</l>
                  <l>As the flame-belching <hi>Cretan</hi> Bull:</l>
                  <l>The Suns meer rays the beaſts more ſmartly ſting</l>
                  <l>Than all the Gad-flyes which they bring.</l>
                  <l>The ſcorched Race-horſe now would fain out-run</l>
                  <l>The fiery Courſers of the Sun:</l>
                  <l>Though conſecrated once unto that God,</l>
                  <l>He ſo much fears his flaming Whip and Rod,</l>
                  <l>He'd rather through the <hi>Ruſſian</hi> Snow</l>
                  <l>With heavie Sled long Winter-journeys go,</l>
                  <l>Than made immortal in the heaven-highway,</l>
                  <l>Draw the illuſtrious Chariot of the day.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="18">
                  <pb n="149" facs="tcp:170736:81"/>
                  <head>XVIII.</head>
                  <l>The Winter-thriving Rabbets curſe</l>
                  <l>Their once-more-friendly Furs:</l>
                  <l>Though no Guns lightning reach their fearful eye,</l>
                  <l>From the Suns fire away they flie;</l>
                  <l>In their deep holes, to ſave their lives, they buried lie:</l>
                  <l>Their barren Warrens may unheeded burn,</l>
                  <l>To ſee their loſs they'll not return:</l>
                  <l>The ſweeteſt ſhorteſt graſs, their chief delight,</l>
                  <l>From their cool holes would now not one invite,</l>
                  <l>Although ſecured from the ravenous Kyte.</l>
                  <l>The Kyte, that with the Sun did uſe to play,</l>
                  <l>And meet his rays half way,</l>
                  <l>Flies to the ſhade, and fears her ſelf to be his prey.</l>
                  <l>The ſharpeſt-ſighted Eagle dare no more</l>
                  <l>Upon his luſtre pore;</l>
                  <l>No more her young one that way doth ſhe try;</l>
                  <l>She from his heat her ſelf doth flie;</l>
                  <l>Her body cannot bear't, much leſs her tender eye.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="150" facs="tcp:170736:82"/>With gaudieſt colours Birds aray'd,</l>
                  <l>Do hide their bravery in the ſhade:</l>
                  <l>Others in vain ſome refuge ſeek to finde,</l>
                  <l>By courting, Stanniel-like, the winde:</l>
                  <l>No ſuccour thence is to be got;</l>
                  <l>The winde it ſelf blows hot:</l>
                  <l>None but the Water-fowl for happie go,</l>
                  <l>Who hide themſelves where ſhady rivers flow:</l>
                  <l>The Swans, the Geeſe, the Ducks, the Drakes,</l>
                  <l>And others who frequent ponds, rivers, lakes;</l>
                  <l>Theſe live what all their fellows wiſh,</l>
                  <l>The life of bleſſed Fiſh:</l>
                  <l>Theſe can defie the heat, whilſt all the reſt</l>
                  <l>Die Phoenix-like, each burnt in his own neſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="19">
                  <head>XIX.</head>
                  <l>But all thoſe pains which ſingly do infeſt</l>
                  <l>That Plant, this Bird or Beaſt,</l>
                  <l>On more unhappie man concentred light,</l>
                  <l>On him they wreak their utmoſt ſpight:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="151" facs="tcp:170736:82"/>The worlds epitome can ſhew</l>
                  <l>All the ſharp griefs the greater world doth know:</l>
                  <l>Nay, all its ills to him are worſe;</l>
                  <l>Their union does augment their force.</l>
                  <l>The ſweating Country-ſwain</l>
                  <l>Feels not alone his proper pain;</l>
                  <l>The numerous miſchiefs that ſurround</l>
                  <l>His Farm, do all on him rebound:</l>
                  <l>There his parcht Corn, here growing Hay appears,</l>
                  <l>And theſe in vain he waters with his tears:</l>
                  <l>Here a ſick Ox, or dying Cow,</l>
                  <l>Does lamentably low;</l>
                  <l>And from his breſt their piteous moan</l>
                  <l>Re-ecchoes in a ſadder groan:</l>
                  <l>The many acres of his barren field</l>
                  <l>Of grief alone a plenteous harveſt yield.</l>
                  <l>But leſt that burnt ground make corn ſcant,</l>
                  <l>And bread the greedy multitude ſhould want,</l>
                  <l>A Plague is rais'd by the ſame power,</l>
                  <l>The numerous eaters to devour.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="152" facs="tcp:170736:83"/>Nor doth Death now his prey</l>
                  <l>With ſingle darts, as heretofore, deſtroy.</l>
                  <l>The Sythes that ruſty to the walls were laid,</l>
                  <l>By the dire heat to th' Country uſeleſs made,</l>
                  <l>Death to the City hath convey'd;</l>
                  <l>Theſe round him with quick hands he throws;</l>
                  <l>Whole houſes down at once, whole ſtreets alone he mows.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="20">
                  <head>XX.</head>
                  <l>But all theſe Sythes for Death do prove too few;</l>
                  <l>Nor will he ſtay for new:</l>
                  <l>Each wounded prey</l>
                  <l>His weapon is ten more to ſlay.</l>
                  <l>'Tis not alone at Sea, where our brave Fleet</l>
                  <l>Does with the Dutch-men meet,</l>
                  <l>That flaming Fire-ſhips to the Combat flie,</l>
                  <l>And, burnt themſelves, conſume the Enemy:</l>
                  <l>Here too at Land whoere expires,</l>
                  <l>Doth kindle others with his Funeral-fires.</l>
                  <l>New Civil wars again</l>
                  <l>In <hi>England</hi> raign:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="153" facs="tcp:170736:83"/>Strange Civil wars, where ſtill</l>
                  <l>The Victors die, and Vanquiſht kill!</l>
                  <l>Now at noon-day none dares to walk that Town,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe midnight-ſafety gains her ſuch renown.</l>
                  <l>A murderer men fear to meet</l>
                  <l>In the moſt large frequented ſtreet.</l>
                  <l>In vain each houſe ſhut up a Jayl is made,</l>
                  <l>In which the numerous Homicides are laid:</l>
                  <l>For there pent up, their killing breath</l>
                  <l>Brings to each other ſurer death.</l>
                  <l>Theſe priſons too, to ſome,</l>
                  <l>The cauſe of further crimes become.</l>
                  <l>The father haſtning to the grave,</l>
                  <l>Bereaves his children of that life he gave:</l>
                  <l>His deathbed-bleſſings curſes are,</l>
                  <l>With which he kills his Heir.</l>
                  <l>Thus doth this more-than-Tyrant heat,</l>
                  <l>To make their miſeries compleat,</l>
                  <l>With ſimple Tortures not content,</l>
                  <l>Adde guilt, and make each pain a puniſhment.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="154" facs="tcp:170736:84"/>Thoſe who firſt innocently ſick did lie,</l>
                  <l>As Criminals do juſtly die:</l>
                  <l>Yet ev'n the Cities unaſſiſted heat</l>
                  <l>To th' uninfected ſeems ſo great,</l>
                  <l>That they, though pain'd with torments and with faults,</l>
                  <l>Envie the very dead their cool and ſhady vaults.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="21">
                  <head>XXI.</head>
                  <l>All theſe dire pains with which the Summers ſpight</l>
                  <l>Plagues others, heighten our delight;</l>
                  <l>Whilſt round about us everywhere</l>
                  <l>They to our fancies or our eyes appear,</l>
                  <l>Our ſingular cool pleaſures they endear.</l>
                  <l>But ah how ſhort a date</l>
                  <l>Is on great joys beſtow'd by Fate!</l>
                  <l>Already does the diſmal Bell</l>
                  <l>Seem to ring our common Knell:</l>
                  <l>For 'tis to death it bids us come,</l>
                  <l>Whilſt that it calls us home:</l>
                  <l>Nay, ours is worſe ev'n than thoſe ſinners death</l>
                  <l>Who midſt their crimes reſigne their breath.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="155" facs="tcp:170736:84"/>They onely from ſmall pains to greater ſell,</l>
                  <l>But we from heaven paſs to hell;</l>
                  <l>Such we account that air which yet</l>
                  <l>Burns, though the flaming Sun be ſet:</l>
                  <l>All enter 't with unwilling feet;</l>
                  <l>Each takes his Shirt as 'twere his Winding-ſheet:</l>
                  <l>Home with delaying haſte we go;</l>
                  <l>Our cloathes half on, looſly about us flow:</l>
                  <l>Yet though prepared ſo for bed,</l>
                  <l>On reſtleſs Pillows none dare lay his head:</l>
                  <l>All are ſick-beds, not Down it ſelf can pleaſe;</l>
                  <l>The heat makes ev'n its ſoftneſs a diſeaſe.</l>
                  <l>In vain we call on Sleep:</l>
                  <l>His <hi>Lethe</hi> which ſo ſilent by did creep,</l>
                  <l>Onely becauſe it was ſo deep,</l>
                  <l>Is to the bottom dry, nor can it keep</l>
                  <l>One precious drop wherein our eyes to ſteep:</l>
                  <l>This makes us, though we grudged not their gold,</l>
                  <l>For which reſt onely is not ſold,</l>
                  <l>To envie the <hi>Ormuſians</hi> wit,</l>
                  <l>Who have by it</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="156" facs="tcp:170736:85"/>Learnt from the Sun, their mortal enemy,</l>
                  <l>This uſeful policie,</l>
                  <l>In water every night to lie.</l>
                  <l>Ah that I ſo might ſleep, not on</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Parnaſſus,</hi> but in <hi>Helicon!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>This onely my <hi>Pindaericks</hi> do deſire,</l>
                  <l>Not for to ſave my houſe, but my own ſelf from fire.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pindar</hi>'s bright Poetick flame</l>
                  <l>Surviv'd his aſhes, blown by Fame;</l>
                  <l>And ev'n his <hi>Thebes</hi> orecomers overcame:</l>
                  <l>It made them ſpare his houſe alone;</l>
                  <l>When all the Citie flam'd, that onely brighter ſhone.</l>
                  <l>But I, alas, who breathleſs ſtrive in vain</l>
                  <l>To reach his noble ſtrain,</l>
                  <l>When from this heat my ſafety I deſire,</l>
                  <l>Too much from feeble Lines require,</l>
                  <l>Which juſtly fear themſelves to periſh in the fire.</l>
               </lg>
               <closer>
                  <signed>CORBET OWEN.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notice">
            <pb facs="tcp:170736:85"/>
            <head>Books printed for <hi>William Crook.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <head>Printed in the year 1670.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>THe Compleat Vineyard:</hi> or, an Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent way for Planting of Vines in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and making of Wines, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> By <hi>W. Hughs.</hi> Price 1<abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr> 6<abbr>
                     <hi>d.</hi>
                  </abbr> Edition 2. with Additions.</item>
               <item>A Deſcription of the Siege of <hi>Candia.</hi> pr. 1<abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr>
               </item>
               <item>Deaf and Dumb mans diſcourſe. pr. 1<abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr>
               </item>
               <item>Jeſuites Morals, <hi>fol.</hi> pr. 10<abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Des Cartes</hi> Life, <hi>Engl. Octavo.</hi> pr. 1<abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr>
               </item>
               <item>A Sermon at the Funeral of a man drown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in a Pit: wherein accidental death is handled. pr. 1<abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>In the year 1671.</head>
               <item>Sir <hi>Henry Blount</hi>'s Voyage into the <hi>Levant.</hi> pr. 1<abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Hobbes</hi>'s Three Papers preſented to the Royal Society, againſt Dr. <hi>Wallis.</hi> pr. 6<abbr>
                     <hi>d.</hi>
                  </abbr>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Hobbes</hi>'s <hi>Roſetum Geometricum.</hi> pr. 3<abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>In the year 1672.</head>
               <item>The <hi>Flower-Garden:</hi> Shewing how all ſorts of Flowers are to be ordered. Edit. 2. with Additions. By <hi>W. Hughes.</hi> pr. 1<abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr>
               </item>
               <item>The <hi>American Phyſician.</hi> By <hi>W. Hughes.</hi> pr. 1<abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr>
               </item>
               <item>Biſhop <hi>Corbet</hi>'s Poems, Edit. 3. pr. 1<abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Court of Curioſity,</hi> Edit. 2. with Additions. <hi>Twelves.</hi> pr. 2<abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr>
               </item>
               <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:170736:86"/>
                  <hi>White Devil.</hi> A Play. pr. 1<abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Old Troop.</hi> A Play. pr. 1<abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr>
               </item>
               <item>Memoires and Adventures of <hi>Sylvia.</hi> pr. 2<abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Lux Mathematica:</hi> Wherein the twenty years Controverſie betwixt Mr. <hi>Hobbes</hi> and Doctor <hi>Wallis,</hi> in the Mathematicks, is deba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and ſtated, by <hi>R.R.</hi> pr. 5<abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>In the year 1673.</head>
               <item>The great Law of Nature of Self-preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion examined, and vindicated from Mr. <hi>Hobbes</hi> his Abuſes. pr. 1<abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr>
               </item>
               <item>The Travels of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lyſſes.</hi> By <hi>Tho. Hobbes.</hi> pr. 1<abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>In the year 1674.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Principia &amp; Problalemata aliquot Geome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trica, ante deſperata, nunc breviter explicata &amp; demonſtrata.</hi> pr. 2<abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Calliope's Cabinet opened and reviewed:</hi> Wherein Gentlemen of what quality ſoever may know how to adorn themſelves for Feaſtings, Funerals, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and all Heroick Meetings. Alſo, the Precedencie of Kings, the degrees, titles and diſtinctions of all Honours, with the Orders of all Knighthood: with a Dictionary to explain all Charges, Deviſes, and Herald-terms, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This ſecond Edition much enlarged. pr. 8<abbr>
                     <hi>d.</hi>
                  </abbr>
               </item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:170736:86"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
